<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Satan the leader in chief to all who resist the reparation of Sion. As it was cleared in a sermon to the Honourable House of Commons at their late solemn fast, Febr. 28. 1643. By Robert Baylie, minister at Glasgow. Published by order of the House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Baillie, Robert, 1599-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77480</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E35_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209954</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868799</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868799</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154625</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77480)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154625)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 6:E35[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Satan the leader in chief to all who resist the reparation of Sion. As it was cleared in a sermon to the Honourable House of Commons at their late solemn fast, Febr. 28. 1643. By Robert Baylie, minister at Glasgow. Published by order of the House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Baillie, Robert, 1599-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 28, 33-54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Gellibrand, at the Brasen Serpent in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643 [i.e. 1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing has publication year 1643[4]; Thomason catalogue lists under 1644.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary order to print.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Zechariah III, 1-2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154625:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SATAN THE Leader in chief to all who reſiſt <hi>THE</hi> REPARATION <hi>OF</hi> SION. As it was cleared in a Sermon to the Honourable Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> at their late ſolemn Faſt, <hi>Febr.</hi> 28. 1643. By <hi>ROBERT BAYLIE,</hi> Miniſter at Glaſgow.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Publiſhed by Order of the Houſe of Commons.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Micah 6.9. and 7.8, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lords voice cryeth unto the City, and the man of wiſdome ſhall ſee thy name, heare ye the rod, and who hath appointed it.</p>
               <p>Rejoice not againſt me, O mine enemy: when I fall, I ſhall ariſe; when I ſit in darkneſſe, the Lord ſhall be a light unto me.</p>
               <p>I will beare the indignation of the Lord, becauſe I have ſinned againſt him, untill he plead my cauſe, and execute judgment for me: he will bring me forth to the light, and I ſhall behold his righteouſneſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for SAMUEL GELLIBRAND, at the Braſen Serpent in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:154625:2"/>
            <opener>
               <date>Die Mercurii 28. Febr. 1643.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>IT is this day Ordered by the Commons Houſe of Parliament, That Mr.</hi> Rous <hi>doe from this Houſe give thanks unto Maſter</hi> Baylie, <hi>for the great paines he took in the Sermon he preached this day at the intreaty of this Houſe, at St.</hi> Margarets Weſtminſter, <hi>It being the day of publike Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And to deſire him to Print his Sermon. And he is to have the like priviledge in Printing of it, as others in like kinde uſually have had.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <p>I appoint SAMUEL GELLIBRAND to Print this Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ROBERT BAYLIE.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154625:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:154625:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154625:3"/>
            <head>For the Right Worſhipfull, his much honoured friend, M. ROUS, One of the Members of the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe of COMMONS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe late times have produced many great and ſenſible changes in many,
<note place="margin">Time a great changeling.</note> both matters and perſons: I muſt acknowledge the power of time, that mighty changeling, over my minde alſo. Some four yeers ago, it was my wiſh, and very paſsionate deſire, then publikely expreſſed, to have had that favour of your honorable Houſe, as once to ſpeak in their audience:
<note place="margin">Ladens: Autocat Praef.</note> Notwithſtanding, the other day, when, in their Honours Name, you did offer to me that ſingular courteſie, how unwilling I was to entertain it, my own heart doth know fully, and you in a part can bear witneſſe. Verily, my former deſires to ſpeak when I could not be heard, were no greater then my preſent to keep ſilence, when I was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>As I would have been very glad in ſo honourable an Audience to have ſaid nothing, ſo when your entreaty, in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great a Name, had neceſsitated me to ſpeak ſomething, I could have wiſhed that what then was ſaid, might have past away without any farther notice: But being it was your deſire that what then was ſpoken ſhould now go abroad, eſteeming it unfit to diſpute any of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
<pb facs="tcp:154625:4"/>in this alſo you ſhall have me obedient.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed therefore to receive what you required of me, the Notes of that poor Sermon, without any addition at all, and without any change conſiderable: It is well if it finde in the eyes of others when read, that patience and reſpect which it had in your ears at the first hearing.</p>
            <p>I know the matter it ſelf is above any juſt contempt,
<note place="margin">The ſcope of the Sermon.</note> for it is not mine, but the Spirit of God's, ſpeaking to the Churches: That of it which belongeth to me, the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of theſe divine Truths, and their Application to the auditor, I leave to the benigne conſtruction of every Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: intreating his belief, it was my ſincere intention, with ſo great ſimplicity and clearneſſe as I was able, To ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to every ſoul, To let out from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Scripture the ſtreams of conſolation on the dry and parcht ground, To ſend down from the Lamps of the Word the Rayes of divine Light, for direction in theſe dark and miſty days: By the terrours of the Lord to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade ſome, To ſmite with the rod, with <hi>the Sword of the Spirit,</hi> the ſecure ſouls of our ſleeping friends, to awaken them; and of our too watchfull enemies, to pull them with fear (but yet with all compaſsion) out of the ſnare of Satan, wherein now they lie captive at his will.</p>
            <p>The Text led me by the hand to that moſt ſeaſonable Conſideration, That <hi>in all quarrells about the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or rebuilding of a Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The chief par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent quarrell are Chriſt and the Devill.</note> 
               <hi>the chief and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parties are Chriſt and the Devill;</hi> Men are but inferiour and ſubſervient agents to theſe two Princes: It is most certain, <hi>That ſide which is for Truth, for Piety, for Juſtice, muſt in the end triumph:</hi> For it is utterly impoſsible, that the Dragon and all his Angels, though for a time and a long time, they maintain the
<pb facs="tcp:154625:4"/>fight, ſhould ever prevail over <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angel and his followers.</p>
            <p>Theſe extraordinary Commotions, whereby not our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom alone, but the moſt of the neighbouring Nations, are at this very hour ſo terribly ſhaken, we truſt they ſhall prove preparations for a glorious Work. At the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Royall Palace, where much rubbiſh is to be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by many hands, where timber, ſtones, and other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terialls, are to be brought together, and ſet in the work by a multitude of divers Crafts-men, no marvell if in that place, for a time, there be much noiſe and ſtirre, much commotion, and ſome confuſion alſo.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe, ere long,
<note place="margin">The end of the preſent troubles muſt be happy.</note> the Scene of this world muſt be cloſed, the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> muſt be beaten from the Stage, which long he hath poſſeſſed; The Rebellion muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the Iron ſinew taken out of the neck of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> The fulneſſe of the Gentiles muſt be brought in with them, that both may mourn after Chriſt their common Saviour. The ſhaking of the Heavens and Earth are the Lords Prefaces and Prologues, his ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Acts, which muſt be followed with ſuch joyfull Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions. When we are moſt toſſed with Tempeſts, when we are moſt likely to be ſplit upon the Rocks of deſperate dangers, then would we caſt up within the Vail the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kor of this hope, the ſtrong Cable of this confident expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
            <p>In the ſubſequent Diſcourſe I glance at one Point which I wiſh were well weighed by all who truely minde the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of the Work in hand:
<note place="margin">The longſome Anatchy of this Church is lamentable.</note> Durſt I have taken the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of prefacing to the whole Houſe, as indeed I was loath to preſume it, having already by the length of my Sermon, taken from them ſo much of their precious time, it
<pb facs="tcp:154625:5"/>would have been all, or at leaſt my main purpoſe, to have propoſed to their Honours, and preſſed that one Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which now, forſooth, is become ſo triviall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the mouth of every one, that it ſeemeth to be rare in the heart, and reall ſenſe of many; I mean <hi>theſe extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary and unexpected delays of ſetting up the Government of God in his Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ordering of the State and Kingdom,
<note place="margin">The firſt care of the State ought to be the ſetling of the Church.</note> how neceſſary ſoever, ought not to precede the ſetling of the Church; In this, the intereſt of God, in that, the intereſt of man is chiefeſt: If any could be ſo impious as to avow their poſtponing of God to the world, yet they would do well to be ſo wiſe as not to marre their own ends, by the miſ-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of their proceedings. Except the Lord build the houſe of a Kingdom, the induſtry of the wiſeſt men is for little purpoſe: And how ſhall the Lord concurre with men in building their ſtate, when men are ſo careleſſe of his Honour and Service, as not to build his Church? <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> laid not a ſtone in the wall of the City, untill <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel</hi> had ſet the Cap-ſtone on the wall of the Temple.</p>
            <p>It cannot without injury be denyed, that the endeavours of this noble <hi>Senate,</hi> for the Houſe of God, have been greater then any Parliaments we ever read of in this Land: That notwithſtanding their exceſsive Labours, the Work is not yet neer an end, it muſt be imputed to all others, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to them.</p>
            <p>That moſt Reverend, Learned, and Pious <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> on whoſe ſhoulders the task of Religion is principally devolved, cannot in any Juſtice be charged with neglect of dutie herein: They have ſo many, and ſo notable witneſſes of their daily indefatigable Labours, that no honeſt mouth will be bold to faſten the leaſt ſlander of this fault upon them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154625:5"/>
            <p>How then cometh it to paſſe, that the Wheels of the Lords Chariot ſhould move with ſo ſlow a pace? This is it which all the godly farre and neer, do vehemently deſire to be taken in the moſt ſerious thoughts of every Religious Member of either Houſe. It paſſeth, I confeſſe mine and every common underſtanding, to hit upon the true and full Cauſe, and the ſolid remedy of this great Evill, whereof the world doth ſee and proclaim, the ſad and ſenſible effects.</p>
            <p>By this weariſome procraſtination to erect the Diſcipline of God,
<note place="margin">The bitter fruits of that Anarchy.</note> that ſo the Laws of the Goſpel might be really execute; it cometh to paſſe, that millions of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, live as they liſt, in <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſſe, Chambering</hi> and <hi>Wantonneſſe, Strife</hi> and <hi>Envy, Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Impietie,</hi> without the controll of any ſpirituall correction.</p>
            <p>Beſide theſe open vices, which like a flood without the oppoſition of any Bulwarke, carry down to hell ſuch a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſouls; there is another more ſubtill device of Satan whereby daily many thouſands are deſtroyed: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and Schiſmes, under the colour of Truth, and more then ordinary devotion, eat like a Gangreen, and Canker, run like a Peſt, from City to City, to the over-ſpreading of the whole Land, without all poſsibilitie of remedy, ſo long as Chriſts Diſcipline is holden out at doors.</p>
            <p>How can it be, but the loſſe of ſo many thouſands, ſo many millions of poor ſouls, which prophaneneſſe and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, daily doth deſtroy, ſhould not cry to Heaven for judgement againſt them, be who they will, who for what reſpect ſoever, are retarders, or but faint promovers of the Lords Ordinance, the onely ſpirituall, the onely proper remedy of all theſe heavy evils?</p>
            <p>There be ſome who care for none of theſe things, the
<pb facs="tcp:154625:6"/>loſſe of ſouls, the flouriſhing of Satans Kingdom, the defiling of Chriſts Crown in the duſt, toucheth not ſo much as the utmoſt skin of their carnall heart; Let ſuch worldlings bewar they feel not ſooner then they expect, the civill inconvenience, which to them alone is conſiderable of that matter whereof we ſpeak. For what I pray ſhould hinder numbers of our people rooted in prophaneneſſe upon occaſion, if they were tempted, to deſert the Cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſide with the enemy for our ruine: Can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy be certainly expected, where piety its onely bottome cannot be found. Alſo what diſturbance may be wrought in the ſtate by the multitudes of <hi>Hereticall</hi> and <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall</hi> people, habituated by long cuſtome in their wayes of errour; It is no difficult matter for wiſe men to prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate, who either from ſtory or experience, are acquaint with the ordinary courſe of humane affairs.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many other the like lamentable fruits of the too too long <hi>Anarchy of this Church,</hi> are a matter of daily diſcourſe to many, but of great ſadneſſe and heavy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, to the children of God: A remedy of them none doth expect, out of Heaven, from any but the wiſedom and zeal of this high Court.</p>
            <p>To theſe who have no experience of the many ſtrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Impediments,
<note place="margin">Too long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation is very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note> whereby the motion of all publike good Works uſe to be retarded, it ſeemeth a prodigie, that the reparation of this Church ſhould ſtick ſo long in the way: eſpecially when they conſider that no Proteſtant Church to this day, did ever ſtay the half of the time in purging the whole Body of Religion, in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and all, as this Land hath already ſpent on ſome few points of Diſcipline alone. It ſeemeth they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed with as many, and great difficulties in their
<pb facs="tcp:154625:6"/>action, as we are in ours: Conſider when we will, <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> or <hi>France, Scotland</hi> or <hi>Holland,</hi> we ſhall finde the hands of their Reformers were fewer and weaker, for all worldly ſtrength, and their oppoſers, whether ye ſpeak of Princes or Clergy, or Nobles, or People, were more and more potent then ours this day: However, we have little reaſon to pretend difficulties from any of theſe quarters: by the mercy of God theſe two by-gone yeers, neither <hi>Prince,</hi> nor <hi>Papiſt,</hi> nor <hi>Prelate,</hi> nor any open Malignant have been able in the leaſt degree, to ſtop the wiſhed Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Such an imputation during the named time, cannot be charged upon any of them: what ever may be ſaid of their will, yet the good hand of our God hath circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed their power within ſo narrow a line, that for any reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of theirs, it was fully in our hands, to have ſet up what ever Church-policie we had found meeteſt, in the moſt, and beſt parts of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I do verily think, if any Church in the World had taken our preſent courſe, they ſhould have found it exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard, ever to have attained to their wiſhed end: If <hi>England,</hi> either in <hi>Edward</hi> or <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes: If <hi>Scotland,</hi> either in their firſt or ſecond Reformation, had ſuſpended over all their Kingdoms the exerciſe of any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, till every <hi>puntillo</hi> thereof had been Scholasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally debated, in the face of an Aſſembly; till every Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter, over and over, had made to the full, againſt every part of every Propoſition, all the contradiction, his wit, his learning, his eloquence, was able to furniſh him: It ſeemeth apparent, that theſe tedious delays had caſten them ſo open, and given ſuch pregnant advantages to the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes of their active adverſaries, as eaſily they had been ſurprized, and all their deſignes cruſhed before they had
<pb facs="tcp:154625:7"/>ended half their conſultations, or ſo much as begun their practiſe; And who knoweth what all this prodigall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and ſpinning out of precious and irrecoverable time, may produce.</p>
            <p>Certainly, this method of proceeding, cannot bring us to any quick iſſue. If theſe points of Government, of Worſhip, of Doctrine, which yet are before us, be handled as theſe that are behinde us, which in themſelves are far leſſe conſiderable then many of the former: If every op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent must be heard upon every point, to object, to reply, to double, to triple his exceptions (as I know no reaſon why it must not be ſo, if we proceed in an equable pace, and our motions to come, be of a length proportionable to theſe that are paſt.) This courſe, I ſay, if constantly kept, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but hold us in hewing of our Stones more then a week of yeers, before we can begin to lay ſo much as the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our Building.</p>
            <p>But I muſt hold, for unaware and unſenſibly, my Pen has run beyond the bounds of an Epiſtle: Your more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary benignitie did invite me to that libertie; It is our comfort, when either, the mentioned, or any other incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience begins to diſcourage us, that God has put in that ſupreme Court, men of your Zeal, Wiſedom, and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; by whoſe deep prudence and induſtrious Action, what to us ſeems deſperate, can quickly be remedied to the full ſatisfaction of all, whoſe underſtanding, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons permit them to be capable of reaſon. Thus praying God to aſiſt every man of your minde and temper, that ſo this afflicted Church and State, may come in Gods due time to a happy end of all the preſent troubles, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips to be commanded, <hi>ROBERT BAYLY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154625:7"/>
            <head>A SERMON <hi>Preached before</hi> The Honourable Houſe OF COMMONS, At the publique FAST, <hi>Febr.</hi> 28. 1643.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ZECHARIAH 3. verſ. 1, 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And he ſhewed me Ioſhua the high Prieſt, ſtanding before the Angel of the Lord, and Satan ſtanding at his right hand to reſiſt him.</p>
                  <p>And the Lord ſaid unto Satan, The Lord rebuke thee, O Satan, even the Lord that hath choſen Ieruſalem, rebuke thee: Is not this a brand pluckt out of the fire?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wiſe Preacher obſerves well that there is no new thing under the Sun,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Intre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</hi> It is a matter of comfort that our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent trouble is no new thing. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.9.10.</note> that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing whereof truly it can be ſaid, it is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new: but the moſt ſtrange accidents of our dayes <hi>have been already of old time which was before us.</hi> This wiſe obſervation was one of the Pillars whereupon <hi>Solomon</hi> ſetled his ſpirit when it was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154625:8"/>much vexed with the ſenſe of the extreme vanity, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable labour, which he had felt and ſeen under the Sunne even in his dayes, which were more then ordinarily proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. This conſideration will be very proper for theſe people or perſons, who after a long proſperity are afflicted with a ſudden and unexpected calamity: while their ſpirit is new and unacquainted with ſuch a variation, it is filled with griefe, with feare and amazement; but when they find that no other thing hath befallen then what often before hath beene, and often afterward will fall out; in place of theſe griefes, feares amazements, patience, contentment and hope, (much better gueſts) begin to poſſeſſe the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe to our firſt Parents the darkneſſe of the firſt night was ſomewhat ſtrange, Perſons who had never ſeene any thing but the light of the day, when the ſhadowes of the night firſt did incompaſſe them, could not be without ſome apprehenſion: yet when at the backe of a number of nights they had ſeen the day ſpring of the morning light conſtantly to ariſe; the darkneſſe of the blackeſt nights was paſt over without feare, and in ſo great ſecurity, as the light of the faireſt dayes. To men who have always lived upon land, when firſt they ſet to ſea, the winds, waves, and ſtormes, are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding terrible; but when they are a little beaten with the experience of tempeſts, their feares doe change into reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and courage. It is of no ſmall uſe to remember that thoſe things which vexe moſt our ſpirit, are not new, but have already been in times before our dayes.</p>
            <p>Unto this ground of courage againſt the vanities and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this life,
<note place="margin">Alſo that it is the worke of God. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.14, 15.</note> the Preacher addes another much more ſtrong. <hi>Whatſoever God doeth it ſhall be for ever, nothing can be put to it, nor any thing taken from it; for God doth it that men ſhould feare before him, and God requireth that which is paſt.</hi> All theſe things which now are, which have already been, and againe ſhall be hereafter, are not onely managed and guided by the good hand of our God but alſo are ſo acted by him, that creatures can neither adde unto, nor diminiſh from theſe workes of juſtice and mercy which the Almighty arme
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154625:8"/>of the moſt High doth daily worke on the earth for this end, that men may acknowledge and feare, may love and truſt in his holy Name.</p>
            <p>The children of God in this land on whom the preſent warre hath brought very heavy affliction,
<note place="margin">Who oft of old hath brought the like evils to a happy end.</note> and who yet are afraid for ſadder conſequents, cannot but be encouraged, if they beleeve that all theſe fearefull accidents are wrought by the hand of their gracious Father in his deepe wiſedome and great juſtice. That as the counſels of the beſt men have not diminiſhed any of them, ſo the plots of the moſt malicious have added nothing to the meaſure wc<hi rend="sup">h</hi> his hand hath mete out. Neither hereafter by all the activity of our enemies, men or devils, ſhall any more trouble be brought upon us, then that which the Lord our God by his owne hand ſhall bring on.</p>
            <p>Alſo that no other miſeries ſhall ever befall us then ſuch as in former times God hath brought about to very happy ends and bleſſed concluſions: for God now doth require nothing but what is paſt, the acts of his providence in our dayes are but repetitions of his ancient proceedings. Were the Lord now to begin to guide the world, we might ſeeme to have reaſon of feare for the iſſue of many difficult paſſages. When a hard piece of worke is put in the hand of an Apprentice for the firſt aſſay of his skill, the beholders are juſtly afraid for a miſcarriage in his young and unexperienced hand; but when the worker is an old maſter of Craft, none are afraid but his cunning hand can act again what ſo oft it hath wrought to the contentment of all the beholders. Were our God a Novice in the great art of governing the world, and of the Church in the boſome thereof; had he to this day never given any proofe of his infinite wiſedome, power, and goodneſſe, in turning about the moſt terrible accidents to the welfare and joy of his Saints; we might indeed be amazed when ever we feele our ſelves ſinking in the dangers wherein the practiſes of our Enemies oft doe plunge us over head and eares: But the Lord having given in times paſt ſo many documents of his uncontroverted skill and moſt certaine will to bring about all humane affaires, as to his owne glory, ſo to the reall good
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154625:9"/>of all that love him, it would be in us an impious and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable uncharitableneſſe to ſuſpect the end of any worke which he hath begun, much leſſe of this great Reformation now in hand, whoſe foundation God hath laid, whoſe wals he hath ſo farre advanced, whoſe gracious and beautifull Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone in his time muſt be ſet on, maugre all oppoſition.</p>
            <p>Theſe two conſiderations are very fit to under-prop a weake mind in its fainting under the weight of griefes and feares,
<note place="margin">Forgetfulneſſe of what hath been, is the chief cauſe of diſquietneſſe. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.11.</note> but behold a third, which if not removed makes both the former without all uſe and fruit. <hi>There is no remembrance of former things, neither ſhall there be any remembrance of things that are to come with thoſe that ſhall come after.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be moſt true that all our preſent troubles of Church and State, be no other but the ſelfe-ſame which in former times have befallen the people of God, and which oft the hand of God hath wrought to a happy concluſion: yet our forgetfulneſſe, our ignorance and inconſideration makes all theſe accidents, and Gods providence about them to be in vain and fruitleſſe unto us, as if never ſuch matters had been.</p>
            <p>For the remedy of this great evill,
<note place="margin">The remedy hereof.</note> the maine cauſe of many minds perturbation and diſquietneſſe this day, to helpe us to know and remember what hath beene of old, our mercifull Father beſide other very profitable hiſtories in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane writs, hath made for us a perfect Regiſter in his holy Scripture of the ancient paſſages of his providence, wherein as in a glaſſe we may behold the cleare Image of our dayes, and by a judicious comparing of what we read, with what we feele, by a wiſe paralelling of times with times, we may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to ſuch patience and comfort in our worſt dayes, as will ſupport us with hope and confidence of a glorious deliverance from all our preſent affliction.</p>
            <p>For this end it is that we have read in your honourable audience this portion of the Prophet <hi>Zachariah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariah</hi> is a patterne of our preſent condition.</note> for as in the whole propheſie, ſo eſpecially in this third Chapter he ſets downe a Regiſter of the eſtate of old <hi>Iſrael</hi> in his dayes, ſo like to our times that we may juſtly take the one for a type, a patterne, a lively image of the other. The people of God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154625:9"/>a long captivity in <hi>Babel,</hi> after many yeers oppreſſion both in Religion and civill liberties, at laſt by the hand of God were delivered: Their <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> tyrants, too ſtrong for their weak hands to deale with, in a ſuddain were overthrowne by the hand of God, ſo that afterwards theſe oppreſſors were never able to ſtand: The poore captives returned freemen in great joy to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> with full hope to ſet up quickly both their Temple and Citie, to reſtore without any impediment both their Church and State to the ancient glory: But incontinently they were troubled with ſo many enemies both at home and abroad, that they gave over the worke begun, and for too long a time fainted in a pitifull deſpaire to get either their Temple or City rebuilded: ſo great were their croſſes and inſuperable their difficulties in their intended and joyfully begun repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that ruined Church and Kingdom; notwithſtanding when all hands were hanging downe and all knees were feeble, when a hopeleſſe fainting had ſtupified and taken away the wonted care of the publike, from the hearts both of their Princes, Prieſts and people, the Lord in mercy wakened them by the miniſtery of two new Prophets, <hi>Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zachariah,</hi> whereby he put againe in all their ſpirits ſo vigorous a life, that they ſet upon the work with ſuch a magnanimous and zealous reſolution as nothing could withſtand them to the very end and perfection of their endeavours, they never reſted till both the Temple and wall of the Citie were fully accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>The viſion ſet downe in this chapter,
<note place="margin">The diviſion of the chapter and the matter of the firſt part thereof.</note> was one of theſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly meſſages whereby that undaunted courage was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired in the breaſts of that otherwiſe languiſhing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged people; you may divide it in three parts: In the firſt you have <hi>the great impediments</hi> of <hi>all their deſignes for the reparation of their Church and State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the ſecond <hi>the removing of theſe impediments.</hi> In the third, <hi>the ground and cauſe of their removeall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt two parts are intertext and woven in together from the beginning to the eighth verſe: the great impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of all their endevours were not men, but ſpirits; were not forraine, but homebred enemies; not others, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154625:10"/>
               <hi>Satan ſtood at Ioſhua's right hand to reſiſt him:</hi> Ioſhua was cloathed with foule garments, with his owne manifold ſinnes, and the ſinnes of the people, whom he repreſented before God: theſe ſins were the fountain of all the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they found from any man; many enemies there were to the Work of God in the midſt of Iſrael, many in the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Countries many in the Court of the King of <hi>Perſia;</hi> but the <hi>Leader</hi> of all theſe was a malignant ſpirit, a powerfull Devill, ſo malapert and impudent as to oppoſe <hi>Ioſhua</hi> before the face of Chriſt himſelfe. Yet neither men nor devills were their principall enemies; the great ſins that notwithſtanding all their troubles the people ſtill did commit, were the ſtrength of the Devill, whereby he ſtopt moſt the progreſſe of the great and gracious work in their hand.</p>
            <p>As for the ſecond part,
<note place="margin">Of the ſecond</note> 
               <hi>the removall of all the named ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions,</hi> this was in the favour of God, firſt in <hi>rebuking the Devill</hi> that was unſatiable in malice; who not content with all the fire of tribulation wherein that poor Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was already made like a Charcoale, a Brand, a Burnt ſtick taken out of the fire, did farther aſſay to burne them to aſhes, and without pity went about to deſtroy them all utterly. 2. That ſtrong hold of Satan, the ſinnes of <hi>the Prieſts and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is broken downe;</hi> the mercy of the Lord freely pardons all their tranſgreſſions. Neither this only, but a third bleſſing is granted, <hi>the graces of the Spirit are poured out upon them for Sanctification;</hi> The foule garments are pulled off, and change of new glorious garments is put on. In the fourth place, <hi>a gracious Covenant is made with Ioſhua</hi> for two things, 1. His continuance in ſervice before God in the temple while he lived, next for a place when he died among the Angels who ſtand in heaven before the throne of God.</p>
            <p>In this is the great comfort of the repairers of Sion, of all the ſincere friends of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> That albeit for a time they have ſtrong and dangerous wraſtlings with men and Devills, they be oft vexed with the guilt of by-gone tranſgreſſions, with the ſtrength of preſent corruptions, with the feare of future miſ-accidents in life, in death: yet at laſt in all theſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154625:10"/>they become more then Conquerours, the Devill by the mouth of Chriſt is chaſed away from further moleſting them, the ſpots of ſinne are waſhed off, as if they never had been on, the ſtrength of corruption is abated, they are clothed and made Beautifull with the graces of the Spirit, they are aſſured of perſeverance and Gods acceptation of continuall ſervice at their hand; they have the Lords Proteſtation that after all their labours for his honour, the welfare of his Church and their mother countrie, they ſhall be tranſlated to an Evangelick felicitie, to ſtand before the celeſtiall throne, injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the face of God and all the fulneſſe of joy thence flowing: when others, the oppoſits of the worke of God, the retarders of the building of the Temple and Citie, ſhall be rebuked with Satan their leader, and caſt with him into that utter darkneſſe where there is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
            <p>The true procurer of all theſe favours was Chriſt the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> to come,
<note place="margin">Of the third.</note> ſpoken of in the third part from the eight verſe to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and his companions were wondred at as mad fools,
<note place="margin">The builders of Sion are wonders.</note> who would venture their peaceable and quiet eſtate in <hi>Babel</hi> with the hazard of a long and dangerous voyage to the deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Land of <hi>Judea,</hi> and when they came there would not reſt in eaſe, but without feare of provoking the great King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> without regard of plottings within by falſe friends, of open armes without by profeſſed foes, not conſidering their owne weakneſſe nor the greatneſſe of the interprize of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a temple, of fortifying a City, went on with courage: this by ſome was derided, by others wondred at:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124, 8.</note> yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves underſtood very well what they were doing, <hi>The Lord of hoſts was with them, their help was in the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Michael</hi> their Prince was a mediatour for them at the throne of God, though yet he was not borne,
<note place="margin">Chriſt the branch.</note> yet in his divine nature he did execute the office of an interceſſor for them with the Father, and the time did draw neere when he was to be brought forth as a <hi>branch:</hi> then he did lurke and lie hid within the vaile of heaven as a roote under the ground,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154625:11"/>yea the ſtock of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> whence he was to take fleſh, was a withered tree in a dry Land: yet he was to ſpring out of it as a branch which from a ſmall twigg was to become a great boulke, wherein all the plants of God behoved to be graffed, that by his fatneſſe <hi>they might flouriſh in the Courts of the Lord and bring forth their fruit in due ſeaſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alſo he is the carved ſtone full of eyes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>branch</hi> was that ſtone which <hi>Ioſhua</hi> did lay in the foundation of the ſecond temple: for Chriſt is the rock wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Church is builded ſo firmely that the Ports of hell may well aſſault, but ſhall not prevaile againſt it; he is a <hi>ſtone with ſeven eyes,</hi> not a dead, blinde ſtone, but living and ſeeing, filled with the Spirit of providence, able to foreſee with a multitude, with a great and perfect number of eyes, all the dangers which can befall that Houſe, and every living ſtone therein which is builded upon him; he is a carved and ingraven ſtone poliſhed and adorned by the hand of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all the perfection of divine beautie: in which the carvings of his fleſh by the wounds of his croſſe, the agonies of his Spirit,
<note place="margin">From his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graving comes our pardon and peace.</note> wherewith it pleaſed the Father to bruiſe him, are not of the leaſt conſideration; for from theſe chiefly flow the two great bleſſings, <hi>Pardon</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> wherewith the Chapter is cloſed. The <hi>Father</hi> for the ſake of the paſſion of <hi>Chriſt</hi> put <hi>away the ſinnes of the Land,
<note place="margin">Revel. 13.8. Hebr. 10.4. Hebr. 10.4.</note> and that in on day:</hi> for the ſacrifice of the Lamb ſlain from the beginning <hi>of the world was of another nature from theſe under the Law;</hi> theſe <hi>though continually offered, could never make the commers thereto perfect,</hi> but he by one offering hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified. Hence flowes a full and perfect peace, they who had been long vexed with a cruell and bloody war, by the Prince of peace are reconciled with God, for their ſinnes in one day being removed by that one ſacrifice,
<note place="margin">Phil. 4.7.</note> the wrath of the Father was ſatisfied: Peace with God brings inward peace of conſcience <hi>that paſſeth underſtanding;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 16.7.</note> and alſo peace with men ſo much as the Lord findeth expedient, <hi>when a mans wayes pleaſeth the Lord he maketh his very enemies to be at peace with him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 1.11.6.</note> The branch that ſprang from the ſtem of Jeſſe <hi>makes the wolfe and the Lamb to dwell together, the Leopard
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154625:11"/>to lie down in peace with the kid, the lion to eat ſtraw with the oxe, the ſucking child to play on the hole of the Aſpe, the wean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed childe to lay his hand ſafely on the cockatrice den:</hi> and theſe men who have been ſpoiled of all, and baniſhed from their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, to returne to their homes, and quickly ſo to proſper there, that they can call their neighbours, as of old, to feaſt and be glad with them under their Vine and Fig-tree, without the feare of any enemy, being ſafe and ſecure under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the <hi>Branch,</hi> the <hi>Prince of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the Viſion of this Chapter, which began with great trouble and danger, ends with as great peace and joy. <hi>Satan</hi> in the entry, with the aſſiſtance of <hi>ſinne,</hi> vexing the Church with all the oppoſition his ſtrength and craft was able to make: <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the end by his paſſion and ſpirit defeating <hi>Satan</hi> and <hi>ſin,</hi> cloſeth the Churches warfare with a happy peace. All theſe things will be grounds to intelligent mindes of many ſweet meditations in theſe times of perplexity; but leaving the reſt, we will ſtand on the two firſt verſes.</p>
            <p>In the firſt whereof we have <hi>the great impediment of Sions reparation;</hi> In the ſecond,
<note place="margin">The diviſion of the Text.</note> 
               <hi>the powerfull removall of that impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment.</hi> The former, for memory and order, may be divided into three; Firſt, <hi>the information</hi> of it, <hi>he ſhewed unto me:</hi> This ſtrong oppoſition which Satan made to the work was ſecret, till God by his Angel opened the eyes of the Prophet <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi> to behold it. Secondly, <hi>its time;</hi> when <hi>Joſhua was ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the Angel of the Lord.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>its matter; Satan ſtood on his right hand to reſiſt him.</hi> Conſider theſe three in order: their ſenſe, the Doctrines ariſing from them, and the Uſes of theſe Doctrines.</p>
            <p>In the firſt, three things muſt be underſtood: <hi>The Informer;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the firſt part.</note> 
               <hi>The way of his Information;</hi> And <hi>the perſon informed.</hi> This <hi>he</hi> who informs, by the moſt ancient Greek and Latine Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters is expreſſed by <hi>the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Who is this informing An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel.</note> but our Tranſlators adhere to the Originall, and juſtly omit that addition to the Hebrew Text; for by adding to the words, they diminiſh from the ſenſe. Doubtleſſe the Lord was the giver of all theſe viſions to the Prophet, but beſide the operation of God, the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154625:12"/>of Angels is here imployed: The Angels are miniſtring ſpirits to the Church and all the Saints, as for many good uſes, ſo for this in ſpeciall, to reveale and declare the will of God to his ſervants the Prophets. That in this place not the Lord onely, but alſo his <hi>Angel,</hi> is underſtood, appeares by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the next Chapter, <hi>The Angel that talked with me, and awaked me, came againe;</hi> ſo in this preceding Revelation he had been with the Prophet, and ſhewed him the Viſion.</p>
            <p>Conſider further, from the firſt Chapter verſe 9. that <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariah</hi> had to doe with three kindes (ſo to ſpeak) of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; one particularly deputed to him for his information, deſigned oft by this phraſe, <hi>The Angel that talked with me;</hi> A ſecond, called, <hi>a man ſitting on a red horſe in the bottome of the valley among the Myrtle-trees;</hi> A third, called, <hi>horſemen on red, white, and ſpeckled horſes,</hi> comming and going as the ſecond Angel imployed them in his errands: Our words muſt be underſtood of the firſt, for the ſecond was Chriſt, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel before whom <hi>Joſhua</hi> here ſtands, who in the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when there is none to help the Church, is mounted on the back of his red fiery horſe, though he appeare not, but lye in ambuſh in the bottome among the trees, ready in his ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to make eruption with his Army of the third Angels, to fight againſt the wicked oppreſſors of his poore people.</p>
            <p>The next word imports the way of information,
<note place="margin">How doth a ſleeping man ſee.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto me;</hi> In the Originall, <hi>He made me ſee:</hi> It was in the night, as is cleare from the firſt Chapter verſe 8. <hi>I ſaw by night, and behold:</hi> The eyes of his body were cloſed, but his imagination was open, ſo the Angel <hi>ſpoke in him,</hi> as it is in the Originall, not to him, in audible ſounds to his eare: The Angel framed the <hi>ſpecies</hi> (as they are called) of theſe things, which are the objects of hearing or ſeeing, or any outward ſenſe within the Prophets imagination. This was an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way how God of old did communicate himſelfe to the Prophets, <hi>by dreamet and viſions, Numbers</hi> 6.12. ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times immediately by himſelfe alone; ſometimes alſo by the miniſtry of Angels; by this meanes a blinde man, a ſleeping man,
<note place="margin">Gen. 15.12, 17</note> may ſee: So <hi>Abraham,</hi> though in a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154625:12"/>deep ſleep, is ſaid to ſee and heare;
<note place="margin">Acts 10 11. Acts 9.12.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> in a trance ſaw the ſheet full of beaſts; <hi>Paul,</hi> though blind, did ſee <hi>Ananias.</hi> Though God alone <hi>who ſearches the heart and the reines,</hi> hath power to worke immediately on the underſtanding, yet Angels, both good and evill, when God either permits or directs them, have power to work immediately on the inward ſenſes both of men and beaſts, as well ſleeping as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and to print upon their fancie all theſe objects, which uſe to be tranſmitted from any of the outward ſenſes.</p>
            <p>As for the third word, <hi>the perſon informed [Me,]</hi>
               <note place="margin">What <hi>Zachary</hi> is this.</note> it is the Prophet <hi>Zachary.</hi> There be many <hi>Zacharies</hi> in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and which is conſiderable, there be two who are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſonnes of <hi>Barachiah;</hi> the one of whom Chriſt ſaies,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.39.</note> that he <hi>was ſlaine between the Porch and the Altar,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Jehojada</hi> the high Prieſt, called alſo <hi>Johanan</hi> and <hi>Barachiah:</hi> Another <hi>Zachary</hi> the ſon of <hi>Barachiah</hi> is our Prophet, ſtiled a young man, the grand child of <hi>Iddo;</hi> that he was not ſlaine betwixt the Porch and the Altar, many reaſons doe prove, which for ſhortneſſe I omit: This is he who by another name is called, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.12. <hi>Jeremy the Prophet;</hi> except you will read that place of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> with the Syriack Tranſlatour, without the word <hi>Jeremy,</hi> for it is hard to admit the corruption of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall Text, by the negligence of the Tranſcribers, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking the contracted word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as ſome will have it; and it is harder, with <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Ierome,</hi> to admit any <hi>apocrypha</hi> parts of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> now not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; and hardeſt of all, with <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> to grant a mnemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick errour, a ſlip of memorie in the holy Evangeliſt.</p>
            <p>From theſe words thus exponed I draw but one doctrine, <hi>That God diſcovers and makes open to the eye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The doctrine.</hi> The moſt ſecret plots againſt the Church will be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</note> 
               <hi>the moſt ſecret plots against his work, and his ſervants about it:</hi> As here, what the divell himſelfe is acting in greateſt privacie againſt <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> is made open. Wicked men have many deep conſpiracies againſt God and his people; Satan joynes his craft to their counſels, when the deeps of Satan are joyned to the depths of crafty men, whoſe heart of it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154625:13"/>ſelfe is very profound, the plot is digged as deep as hell; the plotters become ſecure, and are not feared for any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery; they ſay in their heart, Who ſees us? yet the Lord ſees, and brings all to light for their ſhame: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13. <hi>The wiſdome of their wiſe men ſhall periſh: Woe unto them that ſeeke deep to hide their counſell from the Lord, and their workes are in the darke, and they ſay, Who ſees us? Surely your turning of things upſide downe ſhall be esteemed as the Potters clay.</hi> The wiſe men of this world, by their hid and deep policies, are confident to deceive their ſimple neighbours, by the greatneſſe of their wit to turne all buſineſſe up or downe at their pleaſure; but the Lord by his light diſcovers their deepeſt and darkeſt Mines, by his power he breaks in pieces as a Potters veſſell their ſubtileſt devices: Dan. 2.22. <hi>he revealeth deep and ſecret things, he knoweth what is in the darkneſſe, and the light dwelleth with him:</hi> Proverbs 15.11. <hi>Hell and deſtruction are before the Lord, how much more the hearts of the children of men?</hi> Job 12.22. <hi>He diſcovereth deep things out of darkneſſe, and bringeth out to light the ſhadow of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Scripturall proofe you ſee a cleare reaſon of the point,
<note place="margin">The firſt Reaſon</note> the judgment of God upon the profound Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of this world, who by their wit, aſſiſted with Satans cunning, aſſay to digge their projects ſo deeply under the ground, as the ſhallow wits of other weak men cannot reach them; but behold the plague of God upon their projects, his light ſhines in their darkneſſe, he draws up their deſigns, though as deep as hell; he brings out all their devices, and layes them before the eyes of the Sun, for the contrivers ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſgrace.</p>
            <p>Another reaſon is,
<note place="margin">The ſecond Reaſon.</note> the goodneſſe of God to his people: the helliſh plots of the wicked are to blow them up on a ſudden, <hi>Pſal</hi> 64. <hi>They commune to lay ſnares privily, they ſay, Who ſhall ſee us? their thoughts are very deep, that they may ſhoot ſuddenly at the upright in heart.</hi> The Lord marks all this wickedneſſe, for <hi>he is the watchman of Iſrael who never ſlumbers:</hi> his ſilly ſheep would ſoon be catched, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154625:13"/>his all-ſeeing eye, to which every creature is naked, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes imployed for their cuſtody: The ſeven eyes of the Lord run through the earth to ſearch all the counſels taken againſt the Church, his eyes pierce the thoughts and reines of the craftieſt foxes,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 139. 2, 9.</note> 
               <hi>not a word in any mans tongue but he knoweth it altogether, and their thoughts afarre off:</hi> he found meanes to diſcover to <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 17.16.</note> and to turne into meere folly the counſell of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> once wiſe as an Angel, though after wickedly crafty as a Divell: all the devices of <hi>Syria</hi> were made open to the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 6.12.</note> no word could be ſpoken in the bed-chamber of the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> but <hi>Eliſha</hi> could tell it in <hi>Samaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Uſe of this Doctrine is, firſt,
<note place="margin">The firſt Vſe,</note> for thankfull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment: Who hath diſcovered to us the manifold moſt miſchievous deſignes of the enemy, theſe moſt ſecret and deeply contrived counſels, for the overthrow of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the deſtruction of our Parliaments, the inſlaving of our perſons and poſteritie? who hath brought out theſe works before the eyes of the world? None but that God; who here by his Angel doth demonſtrate to the eyes of his Prophet, the moſt ſecret practiſes of the Divell him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> A catalogue of theſe diſcovered plots would be printed on the Table of our hearts, for the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall praiſe of the mercifull diſcoverer.</p>
            <p>A ſecond uſe is for faithful dependence:
<note place="margin">The ſecond.</note> we know not what our adverſaries this very hour are working under ground: this we know, that they are reſtleſs in their contrivings, like the Sea whoſe motion is perpetuall, not as the heavens for carrying about of light unto the world, but for defiling of the earth by caſting up always upon it new dirt and tangle: like Satan their leader who cannot fit ſtill, but goes ever <hi>to and fro on the earth, ſeeking whom he may devour,</hi> beginning ever ſome new plot where an old one ends. It is good for us to have our recourſe by faith to him, to have our dependance upon him who is acquainted with all their conſultations: when they digge much deeper then we can reach them, were it to the very hell, our God is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154625:14"/>there to ſee and hear all that is amongſt them: we would ſtill be praying that he would bring out their works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that by him we may be ſaved from their ſnares, and carried by their pits, that by his providence we may always eſcape the nets of theſe fowlers.</p>
            <p>A third uſe is for advertiſement of all,
<note place="margin">The third.</note> to be very warie of ſecret contrivances againſt that cauſe which they have ſworne to maintain: let all remember that the ſeven eyes of the Lord are ever upon them in the darkeſt of all their wayes; they ſpeak not the word, they write not the letter in their moſt ſecret chambers, which the Lord can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring abroad to the ears of the whole Iſle for their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſhame: the miſcariage of others ſhould be thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; wilt thou go on in a way of thine own for the hurt of thoſe who are ingaged againſt the enemies of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and juſtice? wilt thou alſo correſpond in a blind and ſecret way to undermine upon never ſo faire pretexts this poore diſtreſſed State? God ſhall find thee out, and as many already have made themſelves infamous, thy ſhame like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhall be proclaimed to this and after ages, ſo much the greater as the evident judgements of God upon many, have not diverted thee from running on to thy own ruine. Some like <hi>Balaam</hi> though an Angel from heaven would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge them from joyning with <hi>Moab</hi> againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet upon the deceiving hopes of wealth and preferment will go on though they ſhould loſe in the end both their life and ſalvation.</p>
            <p>The laſt uſe is for wiſe diligence to have that aboliſhed,
<note place="margin">The fourth.</note> which yet in Gods mercy is covered from the eyes of the world: not to ſpeake of publike miſcariages againſt the Church or State, whereof poſſibly ſome, of whom there is no ſuſpicion, may be as guilty as others who publikely are crucified with deſerved infamy: But to hold upon perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all faults, thou knoweſt not how ſoon the Lord may bring forth not only to the light of his own countenance, but to the eyes of the world thy ſecret wickedneſſe. This is a day wherein thou mayeſt get a cloake to cover thy naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154625:14"/>that thy ſhame may never be ſeen: judge thy ſelf and thou ſhall not be judged; confeſſe with heartie ſorrow, and the Lord ſhall be juſt to forgive; lay hold on that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice whoſe blood waſhes away the ſpots of ſinne; hunger and thirſt for that grace and Spirit of Chriſt, that morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth corruptions: leſt if after this dayes repentance, ſinne reigne in thee, ſeven worſe ſpirits enter into thee, and the Lord bring forth not only before this world but which is much worſe before man and angels in the great congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation for thy everlaſting ſhame, all the works of theſe devils in thee which now lie hid to the eyes of men.</p>
            <p>So much for the firſt part, the information and diſcovery:
<note place="margin">The expoſition of the ſecond part.</note> the matter diſcovered followes, and firſt the time or action wherein <hi>Ioſhua</hi> was imployed when Satan did reſiſt him, he was ſtanding before the Angel of the Lord: for the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of theſe words conſider, firſt, who was this <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the high Prieſt; ſecondly, who this Angel; thirdly, what this ſtanding. For the firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the high Prieſt.</note> this man was <hi>Ioſhua</hi> or <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ioſedeck</hi> the high Prieſt, who returned with the captives from <hi>Babel,</hi> who ſet up the altar upon the baſes before the Temple was builded, who did joyn with <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Prince and ſupreame Magiſtrate of the Jewes in found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and perfecting the temple: theſe two were the two olive trees, which did contribute the golden oil of all the gifts which God beſtowed on them, in advancing the work of the Lord about the State and Church of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Sundry of the Ancients will have this <hi>Ieſus</hi> to be Chriſt our Saviour, but this is a conceit ſo unconſiſtent with ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and many reaſons that it needs no confutation.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Ioſhua</hi> was a Prieſt, for before the death of Chriſt the ſpeciall imployment of Gods miniſters was to offer up thoſe ſacrifices, which were types and figures of that great oblation of the Lamb of God in a true propitiatorie: But when the body came the ſhadowes removed; whoſoever would have the Miniſters of the Chriſtian Church to be truely Prieſts, would by that meanes bring backe the peda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogie of <hi>Moſes,</hi> would ſet up the Antichriſtian ſacrifice of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154625:15"/>the Maſſe, denying in deed as the Apoſtle oft reaſons, that Chriſt is yet come, or hath offered a ſufficient ſacrifice for our redemption. <hi>Ioſhua</hi> was the high Prieſt, Chriſt is the Lord of his own houſe, to order it every day according to his pleaſure: in the new Teſtament he hath appointed all his Miniſters to be brethren and equall, none to be high or a Prince above theſe of his order: but in the old Teſtament the policie is diverſe, for there by the expreſſe command of God twenty four Princes the heads of the families of Aaron are ſet over the reſt of the Prieſts to rule and govern them, and over them all one great and high Prieſt the chiefe of the houſe of Aaron was a type of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This Angel of the Lord is Chriſt the Son of God,
<note place="margin">How Chriſt an Angel.</note> the Patrone of the Church againſt Satan, he who in the firſt chapter ſends out a number of Angels as his ſervants, <hi>Michael</hi> the Prince who ſtands for the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that Prince of Angels,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.21. <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Inde</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>who with his Angels fights againſt the Dragon and his Angels,</hi> ſtiled by Jude the <hi>Archangel.</hi> Chriſt is called an angel, not for his nature, for <hi>he took not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the nature of Angels,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.16.</note> but the ſeed of Abraham:</hi> but for his office; the Father ſent him as a meſſenger to be a mediator of the new Covenant, <hi>Mala.</hi> 3.1. <hi>The Lord whom ye ſeek ſhall ſuddenly come into his temple, even the Angel of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.14. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.21.</note> called by <hi>Moſes the Angel of the Lords preſence, the face of God the Angel in whom Gods name did dwell:</hi> he it was who wreſtled with <hi>Iacob,</hi> who dwelt in the Buſh, he that appeared to <hi>Ioſhua</hi> with a drawn ſword; this great Angel is the Creator of all the Angels, and he in whom they have their ſubſiſtence, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. he is the Prince and head of the Angels, even as Mediator: not for redeeming them from any ſinne, which they never had but for confirming them in grace, which they might have loſt as their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions did, who left their firſt habitation: for to confirme them in their created happineſſe, he has put them in that body whereof he is head, and ſet them in one ſociety with the Saints, making them fellow-citizens of the ſame Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem with faithfull men;
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.22.</note> for <hi>wee come to the company of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154625:15"/>innumerable angels, &amp; to the ſpirits of righteous men made perfect.</hi> This Angel in the firſt Chapter, appears as a man riding upon a horſe, and oft times elſewhere in a humane ſhape,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.31.</note> for <hi>his delight was alwayes with the children of men.</hi> And for his more familiar converſing with men often he put on the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that nature, which in the fulneſſe of time he was to take on, never more to be laid downe: the body wherein he appeared before the Incarnation, ſometimes was reall, created for the performance of ſuch an humane action, and anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilate at that actions end; ſometimes onely apparent, as here where all is but a viſion in the night time, which yet doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hinder the truth of the propheſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſhua</hi> his ſtanding was the geſture of his worſhip and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.
<note place="margin">What is the ſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel.</note> The Prieſts and Levites when they offered their ſacrifices at the Altar, or prayed publikely for the people, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ſtood, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.5. <hi>The Lord hath choſen the Prieſt to ſtand to miniſter before the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 135.2. <hi>Ye that ſtand in the houſe of the Lord, Nehem.</hi> 9.2. They ſtood and confeſſed their ſinnes, and 5. verſe, <hi>Stand up and bleſſe the Lord.</hi> Hence <hi>Elijah</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.1. and others elſewhere who did moſt frequently worſhip the Lord, uſe this phraſe, <hi>The Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom I ſtand.</hi> We take then this ſtanding of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> for the geſture of his worſhip, prayer and ſacrifice for himſelfe and the people in theſe times of deſolation. Some take it of his ſtanding, as a Criminall before the Tribunall of God, where Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan did accuſe him of his ſinnes; this is not incongruous, though it be needfull to take it firſt of his worſhip, for that was his end to approach unto God, and being in this action, Satan comes on him to oppoſe and accuſe.</p>
            <p>At this time the Temple was not built, the Altar of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe was not erected, the Arke of God before which the high Prieſt wont to ſtand, was no more to be found, yet <hi>Joſhua</hi> had ſet up the Altar of burnt offerings before it he might ſtand, as alſo in all other his publicke or private devotions.</p>
            <p>His ſtanding before the Angel was not Idolatry, for this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel was <hi>Michael, One like God,</hi> ever equall to the Father, the Angel of Gods face and preſence; the object of adoration, as well as the Father and Holy Ghoſt: this is the Angel of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Let all the Angels of God worſhip him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:154625:16"/>
            <p>From this Portion thus exponed we obſerve for Doctrine,
<note place="margin">The firſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, In time of publike ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, the children of God are in a praying po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</note> Firſt, the poſture of Gods children in the time of publick dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and miſeries: they ſtand before the Lord, ſupplicating for Sions welfare, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> does in this place: The Temple was lying deſolate, Ieruſalem was an heape of rubbiſh, their faire hopes of Reformation were blaſted, the Enemies of their Church and State were ſo potent with the great King, that by all worldly appearance, they could never be able to wraſtle through their preſent miſeries. In this caſe good <hi>Ioſhua</hi> will not deſpaire, he betakes himſelf to his God, and ſtands before him, praying and waiting from his omnipotent hand for helpe and aſſiſtance to carry on, againſt the oppoſition of men and devils, that work which at Gods direction they had begun, but inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent had found to exceed by much their ſtrength to perfect.</p>
            <p>For this duty there are many reaſons;
<note place="margin">The firſt reaſon.</note> firſt, it has alwayes bin the practiſe of the Saints, <hi>Daniel</hi> Chap. 9 for the deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Sion lies in ſackcloth and aſhes, crying in the 16.17. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>O Lord, I beſeech thee that thy anger and fury may be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned away from this City Ieruſalem, and cauſe thy face to ſhine on thy Sanctuary that is deſolate for the Lords ſake.</hi> Ezek. 9.8. <hi>While they were ſlaying them and I was left, I fell on my face and cryed, Ah Lord God, wilt thou deſtroy all the reſidue of Iſrael in thy pouring out of thy fury on Ieruſalem?</hi> Ier. 18.20. <hi>Remember I stood before thee to ſpeake good for them, and to turn away thy wrath from them. David</hi> in the midſt of his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate agonies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. forgets not the publick? <hi>Do good in thy good pleaſure unto Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Expd.</hi> 32.11. <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.11.</note> 
               <hi>build up the wals of Ieruſalem. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos</hi> lies at the feet of God and wraſtles by prayer to divert wrath from the Camp of Iſrael, he holds up his hands on the mount unto God for the people when they were in fight with <hi>Amalek, Iſa.</hi> 62.1. <hi>For Sions ſake will I not hold my peace, and for Ieruſalems ſake, I will not reſt, till the righteouſneſſe thereof go forth as brightneſſe, and the ſalvation thereof as a Lamp that burneth.</hi> When Sion is under a cloud of trouble, when the darkneſſe of affliction over-ſhadowes Ieruſalem, the godly cannot reſt, they cannot keep ſilence, but impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune their God for the light of a glorious deliverance.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon,
<note place="margin">The ſecond rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> this Practiſe of the Saints is according to the will of God, Ezek. 22.30. <hi>I ſought for a man that ſhould
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154625:16"/>make up the hedge and ſtand in the gap before me for the land, that I ſhould not deſtroy it,</hi> Iſa. 62.6. <hi>I have ſet watchmen on thy wals O Ieruſalem, who ſhall never hold their peace day nor night, ye that make mention of the Lord, keep not ſilence and give him no reſt till he eſtabliſh and make Ieruſalem a praiſe on the eath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third reaſon,
<note place="margin">The third rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> this duty hath the promiſe of a bleſſing both publick and private. Unto the Elders and Prieſts while they are aſſembled, <hi>Ioel</hi> 2. For faſting and prayer is laid out not onely the goodneſſe of God in generall that he is <hi>graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and mercifull, ſlow to anger and of great kindneſſe repenting him of the evill;</hi> but particularly in the 18 they are aſſured he will heare their prayer, and anſwer it, he will have pity upon the afflictions of his people, and be zealous for their deliverance.</p>
            <p>Beſides the publick benefit, the carefull practiſe of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty procures much private good: When the ſalvation of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem breaketh forth as a Lamp, every Inhabitant ſhall not be partaker of her joy. Sundry ſhall ſee it and not taſte of it, as that Prince of Samaria:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.2.</note> when it ſhall be well with the Church, it may be ill with them. As ravenous beaſts and theeves after their roving up and downe in the darkneſſe of the night at their pleaſure, when the morning light doth ariſe, they take them to their dens and caves wherein oft they are hunted to their death. However theſe who now ſtand mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for Sion, ſhall rejoyce in her joyes when they come, they ſhall eat the fruit of their preſent labours, the teares they now ſow in ſorrow, ſhall then be reaped in joy. See an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent promiſe of this, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.10. <hi>Rejoyce for joy with Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, all ye that mourn for her, that ye may ſucke and be ſatisfied with the breaſts of her conſolations, that ye may milke out and be delighted with the aboundance of her glory: Ye ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in Ieruſalem, and when ye ſee this, your heart ſhall rejoyce, and your bones ſhall flouriſh like an herbe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes it pleaſeth not God to relent his anger towards the publicke, yet it goes well in private with the practiſers of this duty: the mourners for Ieruſalem, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9. are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by the Angel and ſaved in the day of deſtruction.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> who vexed their righteous ſouls for what they heard and ſaw among their wicked neighbours, get themſelves and their families preſerved in the day of vengeance: Lamenting
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154625:17"/>
               <hi>Ieremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.14.</note> and for his cauſe his ſervant <hi>Baruch,</hi> and friend <hi>Ebedmelech</hi> are well intreated by the hand of the moſt cruell Enemy; yea, when the wrath of God is greateſt, when <hi>Noah, Iob,</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> are not able to ſave either ſon or daughter, yet they ſhall deliver themſelves &amp; have their own ſoul for a prey.</p>
            <p>Another Reaſon,
<note place="margin">The fourth. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 10.18.</note> the neglect of this duty is a dangerous provocation: When the glory of God goes from the Cherub to the threſhold of the Temple, and from thence to the midſt of the City,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15.</note> and from thence to the mountaine, when the Lord goes to his place that he may be ſought after early, and in his going makes frequent ſtands, looking back if any will ſollow and lay hold upon him that he may returne; if ſo be that none take notice or care of his removall, it much encreaſeth his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: This is one of the complaints of <hi>Iſaiah, Iſa.</hi> 64.7. <hi>There is none that calleth on thy name, that ſtirreth up himſelfe to lay hold on thee:</hi> This is made a great cauſe of the publike calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 42. <hi>I ſought for a man to ſtand in the gap for the land, but I found none, therefore have I powred out my indignation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, I have conſumed them with the ſire of my wrath:</hi> and however God ſhould be good to the publike, yet it ſhall not goe well with the private contemners of this duty, be they more or fewer, be they high or low. Publike men, whoſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar duty is to meet the Lord, and ſtand in the gap, when they ſee the floods of his wrath comming downe to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme the people of their charge, if they run away like foxes to their holes, being careful for nothing but to provide for their own heads, woe and vengeance from God is denounced againſt them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.4. <hi>O Iſrael, thy Prophets are like the foxes in the deſert, who have not gone up to the hedge, neither made up the gaps for the houſe of Iſrael to ſtand in the battell in the day of the Lord:</hi> Therefore in the third verſe, <hi>Woe unto them,</hi> and in the ninth, <hi>they ſhall not be in the aſſembly of my people, neither ſhall they be written in the writing of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> What ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme woe is it to be blotted out of the book of life, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leted out of the Catalogue of the people of God. Neither one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publike men, but the meaneſt of the people are plagued for the neglect of this duty, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.12, <hi>In that day the Lord did call to weeping and mourning, but behold joy and gladneſſe, the ſlaying of oxen, the killing of ſheep, and drinking of wine; this ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154625:17"/>ſhall not be purged from you till you dye ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Uſe of this Doctrine is for your encouragement,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Vſe.</hi> For encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to go on in the preſent exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. <hi>Ier.</hi> 48.10. <hi>Ier.</hi> 14 17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.25.</note> to go on with all diligence in the preſent work of humble ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: You ſee God is well pleaſed with this labour, it hath been the exerciſe of all the Saints on the like occaſion it is the Lords ſpeciall command, he hath annexed to it moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table promiſes, and to the neglect of it very fearfull threats: onely let the work be done with diligence and conſtancie; to doe the work of the Lord negligently procures a curſe: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this day when thou ſtandeſt before the Angel, in all the bent ſaile of thy ſpirit, offer to God the ſacrifice of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and broken heart; <hi>Let thine eyes run downe with teares night and day, for the great breach and grievous blow wherewith the virgin daughter of thy people is already broken;</hi> that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the rivers of blood already ſhed, <hi>the anger of the Lord is not turned away, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill;</hi> that as yet there is no appearance of any cancelling of that Commiſſion which the Lord hath given to the ſword, to bathe it ſelf in the blood of men, without number of all ranks and eſtates. Theſe judgments outward and viſible, are the cauſes of great mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but the ſinnes of the land, that have drawne them from the hand of God, are more lamentable; yet the greateſt cauſe both of lamentation and ſeare, is that great impenitency and contempt of repentance which appeares in the moſt of men: Though the Idolatries, the Adulteries, the Bloodſhed, the Rapines, the Ignorance of God, the profane contempt of the Goſpel and many other crying crimes of this Land, be evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the eye of all; though the great wrath of God be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from heaven, in his moſt heavie judgments upon the midſt, and all the corners of this poore countrey; yet too few doe ſtrike upon their thigh,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.19.</note> to be grieved for what they have done; not to ſpeak of the madneſſe of our enemies, whoſe heart is plagued with induration, their Court, their Clergy, their miſ-led people, running on in their wonted wayes, as the horſe to the battell. If we will look upon our ſelves, we ſhall find that hardneſſe of heart, that carnall and ſtupid ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, doth lye upon the ſpirits of too many. It were very good for the people of God to ſet before their minds the cauſes of that heavie wrath, which long has lyen upon theſe Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154625:18"/>eſpecially to ſearch out the grounds of provocation which moſt neerly concerne themſelves, to make a diligent enquiry of thoſe ſinnes which have bin committed within their doors: with the Lamp of the Word, and the greater light of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to goe through all the corners of thy owne conſcience, and what ever cauſes of wrath thou findeſt there, to lay them all out in an humble Confeſſion, earneſtly ſupplicating for mercy in Chriſts blood, for amendment by the power of the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Spirit, deprecating wrath, and theſe fearfull effects of it, which this day are viſible upon the eſtates, upon the bodies, upon the ſoules, of many thouſands of people.</p>
            <p>This duty alſo would be performed with conſtancy and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance:
<note place="margin">And with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy.</note> thou muſt ſtand in this poſture of Prayer, till that cloud be pierced and diſſolved, wherein God long has wrapped himſelf,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.44. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.49. <hi>Nebem.</hi> 7.3, 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.7. <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.18, 19.</note> that our Prayers ſhould not paſſe through it; <hi>thine eye muſt trickle downe and not ceaſe, without intermiſsion, untill the Lord look down and behold from heaven.</hi> The mourning and ſeparation of the fifth and ſeventh moneth muſt continue all the yeares of Sions captivity; when the Lord brings it back, then, and not before, can <hi>Jacob</hi> rejoice, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> be glad; when the Lord ſhall be good to Sion, and build up the walls of Ieruſalem, then may we ſit down under our Vine and Figge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, to eat of the fat, and drink of the ſweet: But till then, teares ſhould run down like a river day and night, we ſhould give our ſelves no reſt, the apple of our eye ſhould not ceaſe; we ſhould ariſe and cry out in the night, in the beginning of the Watches our hearts ſhould be powred out like water before the face of the Lord, and our hands lifted up to him for the life of our children, our Husbands, our Fathers, our Brethren, our moſt beloved Friends, who all very quickly may be in hazard, if the hand of the Lord be ſtretched out ſtill.</p>
            <p>Every one would be carefull conſcientiouſly to uſe this means, for hereby the meaneſt may be profitable to the diſtreſſed and languiſhing publike.
<note place="margin">The reaſon hereof.</note> When Monies are wanting, none are able to ſupply but the Rich; when Errors and Schiſms are to be beaten in pieces by the hammer of the truth of God, none can be ſerviceable but the Learned; when State diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are to be cured, none can help but the Wiſe; when Battels are to be fought, none can appeare to purpoſe but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154625:18"/>the couragious and ſtrong: But for the duty in hand, which makes more for the curing of our preſent evills, then all that either Wealth, or Wit, or Learning, or Strength is able, by it, I ſay theſe may do notable ſervice who have a very ſmall or no portion in any viſible gift; even poor ſimple unlearned weake women, if they have the ſpirit of prayer and will ſet themſelves to wreſtle with God, they may help to remove the obſtructions and further the cure of the publike miſeries: when all the wealth, wit, learning, force of the kingdom cannot promove the breadth of an inch, our wiſhed ends: every one muſt try and examine his own practiſe of this moſt needfull duty to be grieved or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted according to their performance and care herein.</p>
            <p>A Second doctrine from the former ground, in all our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to God we muſt ſtand before the Angel,
<note place="margin">A ſecond doctrine. In all our prayers we would imploy Chriſt. Iſai. 22.22.</note> Chriſt the Angel of the covenant muſt be interpoſed betwixt God and the ſoul: for <hi>he is the onely way, none can come to the Father but by him, the keyes of the houſe of David are laid on his ſhoulder,</hi> he is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly door: by a wrong door or a right door if faſt locked there is no entrance, <hi>through him we have both an acceſſe to the Father,</hi> Epheſ. 2.18. <hi>We have boldnes to enter into the Holieſt by the blood of Jeſus by a new and living way, Heb.</hi> 10.20.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this is, firſt, the wiſdom and goodnes of our God,
<note place="margin">The firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> who when man by the fall was baniſhed from his preſence and could have no more immediate fellowſhip with him, hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a mid-man for reconciliation to ſtand betwixt him &amp; man, that the friendſhip which could not immediatly be kept, might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed &amp; continued by ſuch a mediation: 1 Tim. 2.4. <hi>I here is one God and one mediator betwixt God and man, the man Chriſt Ieſus; Heb.</hi> 8.6. <hi>He is the mediator of a better Covenant which was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed upon better promiſes.</hi> However we have promiſes that <hi>God wil be our God,</hi> and will receive us as <hi>his people that he will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our ſins no more, that he will give us an eternall inheritance;</hi> yet in him only it is that we have any right to any of theſe promiſes, for he only is the <hi>mediator of that Covenant, Heb.</hi> 9.15.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon,
<note place="margin">The ſecond.</note> when we come alone to our God we cannot be welcome, we are ſo defiled with the guilt of by-gone ſinnes, while we live <hi>ſinne lives in us:</hi> and betwixt the holy pure eyes of God, and our ſinfulneſſe, there is ſo great a contrarietie, that if theſe two ſhould meet without ſome interpoſition, the juſtice
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154625:19"/>of God would be <hi>a conſuming fire</hi> to us. When ever therfore we are bold to draw neer to him, it is neceſſary to have this Angel ſtanding betwixt us, to cover our ſinnes, to divert wrath: by the ſacrifice of his ſoul for ſinne to purchaſe friendſhip, by the ſprinkling of his blood to extinguiſh the flames of wrath.</p>
            <p>A third reaſon,
<note place="margin">The third.</note> who ever will ſtand before God who is to ſpeak to that Majeſty, who is to walk or have any fellowſhip with him, muſt in ſome meaſure be like him,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> holy as he is holy, for <hi>without holineſſe none can ſee his face.</hi> ſuch of our ſelves we are not, we are like to our Father old <hi>Adam,</hi> till we become ingraffed in a new ſtock, till Chriſt become to us a head, it is he that ſends down into us as living members the influence of his Spirit, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, continues, and increaſeth in us that life, that light, that love which makes us like our heavenly Father &amp; <hi>partakers of the divine nature:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.4. Phil. 2.14. Iohn 15.5.</note> 
               <hi>Of our ſelves we cannot think a good thought, It is he that works in us to will and to do; without him we can do nothing:</hi> out of him we are but lifeleſſe, ſapleſſe, withered branches, fit for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the fire, but in him we are <hi>the trees of righteouſneſſe,</hi> bringing forth all manner of fruit in due ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>The uſe of this doctrine is,
<note place="margin">The firſt uſe</note> firſt, for our information of the true cauſe why much of our devotion is fruitles: oft times we draw neer to God but have no acceſſe; we cry and call at the door of heaven, but there is no hearing no opening, no anſwer: The reaſon is, we have miſtaken our way, we have gone to the wrong door, we have run ever alone, in the vehemencie of our owne ſpirit, in the fervour of our naturall deſires: we have forgotten our Mediator, and gone to the Father without the Son; or if we have begun to take him with us, at once as fooliſh children we have run before our guide. No wonder then we be diſciplined for that error, that Chriſt permitting us to aſſay how much we can do of our ſelves without him, we feel our labours loſt, our prayers in vain; no marvell there commeth no voice no meſſage, no fire from heaven on our ſacrifice, to give us any aſſurance of our accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;
<note place="margin">Matth. 3.17.</note> God will not ſhew himſelf well pleaſed with us for any thing we do, when we come without the Son, <hi>in whom alone he is well pleaſed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A ſecond uſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond Uſe is for direction: Hold faſt to Chriſt in all thy wayes, eſpecially in thy approaches to God, moſt of all in thy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Prayers on ſuch a day as this: Set Chriſt betwixt thee and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154625:19"/>God, let all be offered up by his hand, he is thy only Prieſt: no man was permitted under the Law, to offer his own ſacrifice, all was put in the Prieſts hand, who laid all upon the Altar: Chriſt is the true Altar which ſanctifieth and maketh acceptable all that is laid on him. When we draw neere to God by him, he cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all our infirmities, he ſupplyeth all our defects, he enableth all who ſeek their life in him to do every duty in ſuch a way as is well-pleaſing in the ſight of God; he taketh all our deſires and prayers in his hand, put teth them in his golden cenſer, he kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them with his own fire,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 8.3.</note> and perfumeth them with the incenſe of his own merits, that ſo dreſſed, they may have a ſweet ſavour in the noſtrils of the Father.</p>
            <p>A third uſe is for caution: in our magnifying of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">A third uſe for caution againſt the Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians.</note> beware of an old trick of the devill, which of late he hath reſumed, and by it done more miſchiefe then ever. Grace and wantouneſſe in themſelvs are moſt oppoſite, yet Satan ſtriveth to conjoyn them, <hi>To turn the grace of God into wantonneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.29.</note> It is no new thing to adore Chriſt in ſhew, while you buffet him in truth. There is a generation of people who under the colour of magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the free grace of God, of ſetting Chriſt in his Throne, of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing a Goſpel way, of crying down nature, and legall righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: with theſe glorious ſhows, and pleaſant words they are miſled by a ſpirit of deluſion to patronize profanity, to grieve and extinguiſh the Spirit of grace, to ſcoffe at repentance and ſorrow for ſinne, to foſter the fruits of the fleſh, to bring in the higheſt degree of all wickedneſſe, a dedolence of minde, a reprobation of ſpirit; when a man has committed all wickedneſſe with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be nothing grieved for it, as if the Spirit of the juſt Lord were nothing offended with it. Among the many devils, who very boldly this day are walking up and down the land, this is one of the worſt, albeit masked with the faireſt ſhews of piety and reaſon. Who magnifies not the Lord Ieſus, let him be <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema maranatha;</hi> let Ieſus be all in all to thy ſoule, make him alone, <hi>thy Righteouſneſſe, thy Sanctification, thy Redemption:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> but for all that, beware to divide Chriſt from his Spirit, his death from his life, his blood from his grace: Separate not faith from repentance daſh out none of thy Lords commandements ſo long as thou liveſt; wert thou never ſo holy, thou haſt need from thy
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154625:20"/>heart to beg pardon for thy ſins: whoſoever will neglect repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance muſt periſh, who ever will have true comfort muſt be a mourner. Chriſt eurſeth them that laugh now, and no laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more devilliſh then in the act of ſin: he bleſſeth them that mourn now, and no mourning in a child of God more pious then for the offending of God, and grieving of his Spirit by ſinne.</p>
            <p>I thought to have laid open other ſtratagems of Satan, by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the words in hand, and pointed at ſome other very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous errors, wher with lately this land was overgrown, and which to this day are not altogether evaniſhed: Firſt, that Idolatry of the Papiſts, in their ſtanding before Angels and Saints for inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, before images for adoration: further no Papiſt ever went, and thus far Court-Divines here were wont to preach and print.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">Againſt the Arminians.</note> That wickednes of <hi>Arminius,</hi> denying the commerce of the Iſraelites with the Angel of the Covenant, taking away the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Chriſt from the very Patriarchs and Prophets, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Chriſt ſpeak expreſly of <hi>Abrahams ſeeing of his day, &amp; reioicing therin,</hi> yet the Lord muſt have the open lie, and Abrahams both ſight and joy muſt go no further then to his ſon Iſaac, the type of Chriſt; they muſt be terminate in the ſhadow, and not go through to the ſubſtance. It is the leſſe wonder that this man and his followers ſhould ſteal Chriſt out of the Law, ſince under the Goſpel they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally remove him from the hearts of the people, putting free-will in the place of grace, and in ſtead of our juſtification by Chriſt, would teach us that old fundamental error of the Papiſts, juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by works, and inherent righteouſneſs, to wit, by faith as a worke in us. Strange that any Proteſtant Divines ſhould yet ſtumble upon that infamous ſtone.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">Againſt the Socinians.</note> That horrible wickedneſſe of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> denying the Angel of our Text to be Chriſt, becauſe he had no being before his conception; denying his Incarnation, aboliſhing his divine nature, blaſpheming the Trinity: A wonder that ſo foul a ſpirit ſhould ever have gotten entrance in any famous Divine, or other man of note in this Ile, except this were an houre of darkneſſe, wherein all ſorts of devils are crept out of their dens, and walk ſo familiarly with men, that they become bold now to ſpeak of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioning authority for a toleration, that ſo this poor kingdome, not onely in theſe times of confuſion, but for ever ſhould be to them all a place of quiet habitation.</p>
            <p>A fourth of theſe,
<note place="margin">Againſt Popiſh Prieſts.</note> who preſſe on us the office of a proper Prieſt, to offer up in a ſacrifice upon the Altar the preſent body of Chriſt, not caring to bring back with open face into our Church that groſſeſt abomination of Popery, the unbloudy ſacrifice of the Maſſe.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:154625:20"/>
            <p>The fifth of theſe,
<note place="margin">Againſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</note> who from the high Prieſt of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would inferre a Pontife, and an Eccleſiaſtick Prince in the new, by this means not onely bringing back the types and figures of Aaron, the pedagogic of Moſes; but alſo with the Papiſts (the authors of this argument) re-inducing a Dioceſan Biſhop, and a Patriarch above him, with a Pope above all, as Aaron was above the other Prieſts. How farre this is againſt the grounds of the Goſpel, may be ſeen by the moſt ſimple in theſe three plain rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Firſt, Chriſt hath made all the officers of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who are of the ſame order, to be equall, all to be Brethren, none to be a Prince, or in any degree of ſuperiority above his fellows. This is not controverted in the three extraordinary offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, no Apoſtle above an Apoſtle, no high Evangeliſt above a low one, no Prophet ſuperior to a Prophet. This is alſo gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in 3 of the ordinary officers, no Deacon above a Deacon, no Elder above an Elder, no Doctor above a Doctor. That the like is in the ſeventh officer, That no Paſtor is a high and a great one above a ſmall and a low Paſtor; the rule of propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the analogie of things in the ſame kind, will make it cleare. Secondly, the nature and eſſence of Epiſcopacy, puts the power of ordination in the hand of one man, expreſly againſt the Apoſtle, 1 Tim. 4.14. where Ordination is put into the hands of many, for it is called the laying on of the hands of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: however divers expoſitions of the word Presbytery are brought by ſome, yet no man can expone it of one Biſhop.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The nature of Epiſcopacy puts all the Eccleſiaſtick Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of a whole dioceſſe in the hand of one man; but Chriſt, Matth. 8. gives it to many, <hi>Tell the Church:</hi> none ever did expone the Church of one Biſhop, except ſome Papiſts, who underſtand it of the Pope.</p>
            <p>With a good conſcience therefore have your Honours rooted up and caſt out of the Church that evill tree, which God never did plant; what further alſo ſhall be found neceſſary for the full extermination of that curſed weed, if an Ordinance were requiſite to be added to the former Bills, or what elſe the heart of good people can require for their full ſecurity, from the returne of the leaſt degree of that Popiſh government, it is fully expected from your piety and zeal.</p>
            <p>What ſome pleads for the antiquity of this wicked weed, I wiſh they would anſwer ingenuouſly, if any more antiquity was ever alledged by any for Biſhops, then is confeſt by all of Monks and Friers, of Hermits and Nuns, for Abbots and Priors: alſo if it can be ſaid with any colour of truth, that more hurt did ever
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154625:21"/>come to this Church and State by the one, then now is ſeen and felt from the other. And if <hi>England</hi> did never repent to this day for altering the old Laws and caſting out of their Church and State theſe former Locuſts, what greater reaſon can be imagined they ſhall have ever to repent the putting of Biſhops and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendances out of their Laws and Land? All your brethren of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches after almoſt a hundred yeers experience have oft rejoyced, but never grieved, for baniſhing that degree of Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſme. It cannot be denyed but that Epiſcopacy is ſuch a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter of Papacie, that where the one falls, the other cannot ſtand. Pluck up but this one weed in the Antichriſtian Kingdomes over Sea, let Biſhops only be removed from <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spaine, Germanie</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as they are from <hi>Britaine,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> can no more ſtand thereafter then a head can without its body or limbs: the maxime is certaine and demonſtrable, <hi>no Biſhop no Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third part of the firſt verſe contains the oppoſition made to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The third part of the verſe expounded.</note> while he ſtands before the Lord to advance the interrupted work of Sions reparation, Satan is at his right hand to croſſe all his deſignes Three words here are to be expounded: who is this Satan; what is his ſtanding on <hi>Ioſhua</hi> his right hand; and how he reſiſts him.</p>
            <p>Satan is one of the names of that great Angel who <hi>left his firſt habitation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 6.</note> by ſinning againſt his Creator, and therefore with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Angels his followers, was caſt down from the heaven to the lower world to be <hi>reſerved in chaines of darkneſſe to the day of judgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.71.</note> when he is to be bound ſtraiter and to be caſt into <hi>the fire prepared for him and his Angels.</hi> In the meane while he has ſome libertie in his chaine and priſon, he goes alwayes <hi>to and fro and walkes in the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeking whom he may devoure;</hi> he flies in the aire ſpying his prey, ever intent to aſſault mankind, and above all, the moſt godly: for his oppoſition and hatred (which gives him the name of Satan) is moſt againſt God, and for his cauſe, againſt his children, eſpecially Chriſt, whoſe <hi>heele he bruiſed</hi> in his temptations and croſſe: this is he who in the <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.8. <hi>is called the Dragon, the old Serpent, the devill and Satan who with his Angels did fight againſt Michael and his Angels:</hi> this was the wicked ſpirit who tempted <hi>Evah,</hi> who vexed <hi>Iob,</hi> who ſtirred up <hi>David</hi> to number the people, who entred into <hi>Iudas,</hi> and here ſets upon <hi>Ioſhua.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:154625:21"/>
            <p>The next point is his ſtanding upon <hi>Joſhua's right hand:</hi> I will paſſe a number of Allegories, which ſundry of the Ancients bring upon this phraſe, it ſeems without any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery to imply an oppoſition open, but cautelous: I ſay open, for Satan lurks not, he ſtandeth not behinde <hi>Joſhua</hi> his back, but comes up to his ſide, and there appears a profeſſed and avowed enemy; yet cautelous, for he chooſes the place of advantage; the right hand is the inſtrument of Action, it manages the Sword, and every Weapon: ſo, who ſtands upon the right hand, hath the place of advantage.</p>
            <p>The third word is <hi>to reſiſt him;</hi> This was the end why Satan ſtood in ſuch a place, the more eaſily to croſſe and reſiſt all the good deſigns of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> that what ever he did or ſaid, to God or man for advancing the work of the Temple, or any part of the Churches welfare, he by his craft and might did aſſay to countercarve it, and make it fruitleſſe.</p>
            <p>That which here is brought by ſome of Satan his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> we do not deny it as one of the means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he did croſſe the high Prieſt: For he is ſtiled a Devill, an Accuſer, a Calumniator,
<note place="margin">Revel. 12 10.</note> who is ever <hi>accuſing the Brethren</hi> to God, as he did <hi>Job,</hi> ſometimes falſly, and ſometimes truely, but ever calumniouſly, becauſe ever upon malice. The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular accuſation is not expreſſed in the Text, yet the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſts put that in their <hi>targum</hi> on this place, which is moſt likely, That Satan pleaded againſt <hi>Joſhua,</hi> as a man who ought not to be heard of God, or receive any aſſiſtance from him for the building of <hi>Sion,</hi> ſince he and the reſt of the people were clothed with the foul Garments of ſin, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially that one, of ſuffering his Children to marry ſtrange Women.
<note place="margin">Ezra 9 3.</note> The marrying with Idolaters was ſo grievous and dangerous a ſin, that it made <hi>Ezra</hi> lament very heavily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God: <hi>Joſhua</hi> his tolerating of this fault in his children, was a matter of a juſt accuſation, and might have hindered the fruit of his Prayers, and all his endeavours for <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Doctrine obſerve,
<note place="margin">The firſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> That <hi>the great and chief leader of all who oppoſe the Reformers of a Church or State, is the Devill.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:154625:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeſhua</hi> and <hi>Zerubbabell</hi> in their repairing of the ruines of the Church and Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Satan is the leader in chief to all who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formation of a Church or State. Ezia 4 8.</note> had oppoſites of many kindes and conditions, <hi>Ezra</hi> 1. At the firſt founding of the Temple, there appeared againſt them (at the beginning ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and then openly) Firſt, the common people of the Land, the <hi>Samaritanes,</hi> the Brethren of our <hi>Caſſandrian</hi> mixed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, half Idolaters, half Iſraelites: With them joyned the Rulers of the Provinces, <hi>Rehum the Chancelor, and Shim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhai the Scribe,</hi> alſo the bribed Courtiers of the King; and at laſt the King himſelf: This oppoſition did ſo prevail, that the building was marred for many yeers. When the work again was ſet on by the motion of <hi>Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zachariah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 5.3.</note> that ſame prophane multitude, and their Governours, <hi>Tatnai</hi> and <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thar-Boznai</hi> did oppoſe; yet by the help of God the Temple was finiſhed.</p>
            <p>Afterwards they went to build the Wall of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gods order re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, that the Church be ſettled before the State.</note> For this is the holy and happy order of the People of God in their building; to begin with the Temple, and then to go to the Citie, to perfit the Temple before they lay a Stone in the Wall of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> It is prepoſterous to begin with the State, and end with the Church; that order pleaſeth not God, it is not ſuitable to his honour, and will not be bleſſed by him.</p>
            <p>How ever, ſo ſoon as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> began to make up the Wall, there was about him a ſwarm of enemies to hinder his progreſſe, <hi>Tobia, Sanballat, Geſhem,</hi> and not onely theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Forraigners, but alſo many among themſelves that profeſſed friendſhip:
<note place="margin">Nehem. 6 17.</note> Many of the Nobles of <hi>Judah</hi> kept correſpondence by Letters with the enemies, and that in a way well near avowed, and open. Sundry of the Prieſts and Prophets were plotters againſt the work:
<note place="margin">Nehem. 6.14.</note> Some Women alſo are noted for Malignant Inſtruments, by name the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſſe <hi>Noadia</hi> is Regiſtred to her perpetuall infamy,
<note place="margin">The greateſt plot of the enemies of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was a ſubdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</note> for her correſpondence with the enemy, in prejudice of the good work in hand.</p>
            <p>Many plots were ſet on foot to diſcourage the people of God, and make them faint in their labour, when the building
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154625:22"/>was neer an end; but one was moſt likely to prevail, a friendly treatie propounded, by <hi>Sanballat</hi> to <hi>Nehemiah</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending an Union of Counſells, and an accommodation; but intending to kill <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> that the reparation of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> wherein he was the prime Agent, ſhould be interrupted by his death, and quite given over. This plot was aſſayed once,
<note place="margin">Nehem. 6.4.</note> twice, thrice, four times, but without ſucceſſe; for it was the wiſedome of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to diſtruſt them, and never for any perſwaſion, for any terrour, to enter into conference with them, while the Wall was once perfited; and then the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries perceiving without further haeſitation, the hand of God in the work they oppoſed, ſate down in deſpair, and gave over their enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>All theſe oppoſitions from ſo many divers ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, were cleer to the eye of all; yet when God will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to the eye of the Prophet, the great and main hinderer of the work in hand; he ſets all other aſide, and points at Satan alone, ſtanding on the right hand of the chief workers, to croſſe and reſiſt them. It is cleer then, that in all the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition we feel to the welfare, either of Church or State, Satan is he on whom the eyes of the godly wiſe would prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally be fixed.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon of this Doctrine, is this, Satan is the head,
<note place="margin">The firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> the prince, the father, the god of all the enemies of the Church, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>I will put enmitie betwixt thee and the woman, betwixt her ſeed, and thy ſeed.</hi> The fountain of all the enmitie of the wicked againſt the Church, is here made the Serpent, deriving his malice to men, as to his ſeed and poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. The wicked in their malicious actions againſt Chriſt and his Church, are reputed the children of Satan, and worke according to the nature of their father:
<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.44.</note> 
               <hi>You are of your father the devill, the luſts of your father you will do.</hi> When the wicked are not ready enough to follow the motions of Satan againſt the Church, as children to be directed by their fathers advice, then like a Prince or Tyrant doth he drive them, as captive ſlaves, to commit miſchiefs: For this <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. he is called, <hi>the Prince of the power of the Aire, the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154625:23"/>ſpirit that now worketh in the children of diſobedience.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. <hi>The wicked are in the ſnare of the devill, taken captive by him at his will:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4 4.</note> 
               <hi>He is the god of this world:</hi> When ſervants do the commands of their maſters, what ſubjects or children are ſet upon by their prince or father, what is done by members by the motion of the ſpirit that animates and moves them, all theſe actions muſt be aſcribed chiefly unto their principall agents.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon is,
<note place="margin">The ſecond Reaſon.</note> The intereſt of Satan in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions of a Church and State is greateſt: Intereſt, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, loſſe, make perſons active: when a State is confounded, and a Church in trouble, there is no reſtraint of Idolatry, of Hereſies, of Schiſmes, of Drunkenneſſe, Blaſphemics, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, or any villanie, wherein the dominion and glory of Satan is openly demonſtrate: But when the times of licentious libertie come to an end; when by the mercies of God, the outward State is ſettled; the execution of good Laws baniſheth away theſe abominations; the outward kingdom of Satan is reſtrained and broken: But when with the State, the Church alſo is ſettled, when the Goſpel in its full libertie, puritie, and power is ſet up, then the ſtrongeſt Caſtles of Satan are invaded, Chriſt entereth the inmoſt Cabines of the heart, and ſubdueth every imagination to his knowledge, and reformeth not onely the outward man, but by bringing his heavenly Light and Life to the ſoul, maketh the heart humble, chaſte, wiſe, ſpirituall, and ſo ſubject to the Spirit of Chriſt, that Satan gets no more peace in any room of his former poſſeſſion? No wonder then, that this craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſpirit foreſeeing theſe evident loſſes, and clear diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages which the ſettling of a Church and State will certainly bring upon him, he aſſay with all his might to continue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and confuſion, for in theſe lies the ſtrength of his kingdom.</p>
            <p>The uſe of this Doctrine is.
<note place="margin">The firſt Uſe.</note> 1. For affrighting of all theſe who oppoſe Reformation of Church or State, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding from hence what ſpirit leadeth them: For it is cleer, that not they onely, who upon the conſcience of their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154625:23"/>miſ-deſerving to ſave themſelves from the legall puniſhment of their crimes, or otherwiſe blinded by avarice and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, upon deſire and hope of theſe profits and places whereof they deſpaired in regular times, for theſe baſe ends have been prime counſellers in the firſt conceiving of this lamentable rupture betwixt the Prince and his beſt ſubjects; but alſo all they, who either openly have divided from us in ſiding with that evil faction, or remaining among us in perſon, by their means or counſels do oppoſe the building of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the rearing up the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> The leader of all theſe oppoſites appeareth to be that moſt malignant ſpirit, the devill. We deny not that ſundry of theſe men for their opinions and practices wherein they differ from us, may have very ſtrong and plauſible arguments; yet they would remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that Satan oft times, by <hi>ſtrong deluſions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ 2.11.</note> maketh his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers <hi>believe lies.</hi> We grant alſo, that ſundry of the elect children of God, before their calling, in the dayes of their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, may be withdrawn to ſerve the devill, in the moſt wicked employments againſt God; <hi>Father, forgive them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 23 34.</note> (ſaith Chriſt of many of his crucifiers) <hi>for they know not what they do.</hi> Yea, for a time, the very regenerate, and theſe who otherwiſe walk with God, by the violence or ſubtilty of a tentation, may be driven to a very evil way, and may engage themſelves in the worſt ſervices of Satan, and oppoſe in their deſires, counſells and actions the moſt bleſſed works of God. Chriſt admoniſheth the chiefeſt of his Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Luk 9 55. Matth. 16 23,</note> that they <hi>knew not of what ſpirit they were:</hi> And to <hi>Peter</hi> he ſaith plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That the devil, from his mouth, did tempt him to ſpare himſelf; which was no other, then to give over the Work of mans Redemption.</p>
            <p>However all theſe things may be, yet all who are in the actuall ſervice of Satan, againſt God, have great reaſon of fear, for their preſent condition: If God come upon thee in thy act of reſiſting his ſervants in his Work, his hand may ſuddenly daſh thee in pieces, as it hath done many already, like a Potters veſſell. How fearfull a thing is it to be ſerving the devill! what can men expect for their wages, except they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154625:24"/>recover themſelves out of his bonds, wherein now they lie captive like Gally-ſlaves, but a part with their maſter for ever in his horrible portion? O if the eyes of men were opened, to behold the face of their maſter: a clear ſight of that ugly leader, would doubtleſſe move many to lay down their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and with great grief for miſcarriages paſt, to ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to redeem the time, with all diligence to employ heart, hand, means, and all God hath given them, for the further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the building of Sion, which too long, by Satans powerfull conduct, they have endeavoured to retard.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Uſe is for compaſſion thus far,
<note place="margin">The ſecond Uſe.</note> on the worſt of our oppoſites, as to take them but for inferiour inſtruments, acted and driven on by a mighty leader: let the edge of our ſharpeſt anger be turned from them, on him: Theſe his blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded inſtruments we ſhould heartily pity, and pray for, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the like nature and weakneſſe in our ſelves, which had not the grace of God preſerved us againſt tentations, might have made us ready to have given up our wit, our will, our hands, our means, and all, to have reſiſted the Work of God, and furthered the work of Sathan, as much as any of the moſt active malignants. It is good to have a meek and compaſſionate ſpirit towards perſons who have ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbd to a tentation;
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>conſidering our ſelves, leſt we alſo be tempted</hi> and overtaken in the ſame or a worſe fault. The Apoſtle gives us hope, that ſundry who oppoſe themſelves to God, being inſtructed in meekneſſe, may peradventure get repentance, to acknowledge their pernicious ways, and to recover themſelves from the ſnare of the devill, though for a time they be taken captives by him at his will.</p>
            <p>A third Uſe is,
<note place="margin">The third Uſe.</note> for continuall watchfulneſſe. The Prince and Generall of our oppoſites is a reſtleſſe ſpirit, who will never give over his malicious contrivings: readily he may change his inſtruments, but never his deſigne: When old in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments become blunt and unſerviceable, or when they break in his hand, he can caſt them by, and take up new ones, more dangerous then the former: though all preſent and paſt plots were diſcovered to the bottom, and fully prevented, yet
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154625:24"/>there remaineth in that prime adverſary a wit to deviſe many more, and theſe ſeven-fold worſe then any yet we have heard of: we would never be ſecure,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.12.</note> having to do not <hi>with fleſh and blood, but with principalities and powers, with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall wickedneſſes in higher places.</hi> Againſt ſpirits ſpirituall Weapons muſt be uſed: Did we ſtrive onely with the craft and force of men, we might hope by wiſedome and policie to countermine their plots, and by juſt Arms to over-power and ſuppreſſe their oppreſſion: But our chief partie being Satan, we muſt put on the <hi>armour of God, The ſhield of Faith, The helmet of Hope, The breſt-plate of Righteouſneſſe;</hi> and, above all, that Catholike weapon of prayer. In theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats, the weakeſt may do greateſt ſervices: many, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not go to the Fields for fighting, to the Houſes for counſell, to the Aſſembly for diſputation, yet may hold up their hands on the mountain with <hi>Moſes,</hi> may wreſtle with God as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> may ſtand before the Angel with <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and by the means of the Angel get Satan our prime enemy defeat: when <hi>Goli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath</hi> the Captain doth fall, the reſt of the Philiſtims his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers will not long ſtand. However, this Church and State, in theſe dayes of darkneſſe, are moſt helped by them who ſet their faces truely to ſeek the Lord for the Land, in Faſting and Praying, with Faith and Sanctification: one of theſe is more precious then a thouſand others, who, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their fighting and diſputing for the common Cauſe, do continue to grieve the good Spirit of God, to ſtrengthen the hand of Satan againſt us, going on, after all theſe publike Humiliations, in their wonted courſe of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, neglecting the mortification of their ſecret luſts, and all carefull walking with God in the Spirit of their minde, to any true pleaſing.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Obſervation might be made on this paſſage,
<note place="margin">A ſecond Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Satan oppoſeth moſt our prayers for Sion.</note> That Satan his invaſion of the godly is moſt in their Worſhip, and ſpecially in their prayers for the publike; as here he reſiſteth <hi>Joſhua,</hi> when he is ſtanding before God to petition for the ruined eſtate of Sion.</p>
            <p>No wonder the people of God, at theſe ſolemn times of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:154625:25"/>publike Supplications,
<note place="margin">The godly moſt diſtracted with temptations in time of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Gen. 15.11. Matth. 13.4.</note> fall ſhort of their intended ſervices; That their hearts come not up to their deſires in the acts of Worſhip; That vageing of minde, hardneſſe of heart, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe of hearing, lie hardeſt then upon them: The reaſon is, Satans ſpeciall attendance at theſe occaſions above any. The ravenous birds wait upon <hi>Abraham</hi> onely at his Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; the fowls go out with the ſower to pick up the good Seed, to make the Word and the Worſhip unprofitable. Our heart of it ſelf is very earthly, carnall, dead, and vain; yet beſides all its inward Malignitie, Satan by his tentations, ſtrives to inſpire it at theſe holy times with ſo much of his ſupernaturall wickedneſſe, as he is able. It ſhould adde to our grief, when our ſenſible miſcarriage in ſo holy an exerciſe demonſtrateth, not onely the preſence of a devill with us, but alſo his prevalence over us for our great hurt: Alſo it is a matter of ſingular comfort when we get grace to diſcharge ourſelves of theſe ſolemn ſervices, in ſome meaſure accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: When with a Spirit enlightned, enlivened, enflamed, melted from above, we get our ſouls poured out before God, for the publike ſins, and publike diſtreſſes: When with an holy, an honeſt, and vigorous bent-ſail of ſpirit, we have begged mercy, and what elſe we conceive needfull for our ſelves and others: When in an attentive and faithfull heart, we receive the heavenly Seed of the Word, and feel our ſelves thereby ſtrengthned to walk in the wayes of God, to mourn for, and fight againſt the corruptions of our heart, and life. This is a matter of joy for this cauſe among others, that hereby we obtain a ſenſible victory over that ſtrong ſpirit, who hath not been able, as oft at other times, to deprive us of the comfort and fruit of the Worſhip. Chriſt who at ſuch a time maketh thee clearly victorious over Satan, ſhall ſhortly make thee to triumph, and tread him under thy feet.</p>
            <p>A third Obſervation might here alſo be pointed at,
<note place="margin">A third Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Satan reſiſteth moſt the Miniſters of Gods houſe.</note> if time did not ſtrait; Satan his ſpeciall malice is againſt <hi>Joſhua</hi> the high Prieſt; his ſpeciall enmitie is againſt the ſervants of Gods Houſe; the Meſſenger of Satan buffeteth <hi>Paul;</hi> it was
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:154625:25"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi> and the Apoſtles that Satan ſought to winnow,
<note place="margin">2 Co. 12.7. Lu6e 22.31.</note> and ſift as Wheat.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon is, They are the Paſtors of Gods flock;
<note place="margin">The Reaſon.</note> when the Shepheard is ſtricken, the flock will be ſcattered: They are the Stewards of Gods Houſe; If the Steward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come unfaithfull, the children of the family will be in danger of ſtarving: They are the Officers of Gods Army; if the Leaders and Standard-Bearers fall, the Souldiers will ſoon be put to the flight: They are the light of the World, if the Lamps be extinguiſhed, the Houſe ſitteth in darkneſſe, and the ſhadow of death: They are the Salt of the Earth, if they become unſavoury, the people are in danger to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a polluted and unſavoury Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>Great care would be had for the aſſiſtance and comfort of the ſervants of Gods Houſe;
<note place="margin">The Uſe.</note> the people would bear them in their hearts before God, and pray for the abundance of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace upon them: the grace of God on the Paſtors, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the benefit of the people; the oyntment poured on the head of <hi>Aaron</hi> dropped down to his feet, and drenched the loweſt borders of his garment: When the Lord clothes his Prieſts with Righteouſneſſe and Salvation, then do all the Saints ſhout aloud for joy: the people not onely by their prayers to God would aſſiſt and hold up the weary hands of their Paſtors, as <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> did the hands of <hi>Moſes;</hi> but alſo, by their loving countenance, their liberall maintenance, their ready obedience, would give them all encouragement; <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. <hi>They watch for your ſoul; obey them therefore, that they may do their work with joy, and not with grief, for that is unprofitable for you.</hi> When moſt of the day, and much of the night they have been with God on the Mount for your welfare; when much of their time hath been ſpent in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating with Satan for the ſafety of your ſoul, Is it meet that they ſhould be grieved,
<note place="margin">The honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſes would ſee to the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods ſervants.</note> or their hands weakned by your neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of them, or miſcarriage towards them?</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe it will be the ſpeciall care of this religious and wiſe Senate, to eſtabliſh ſuch Orders in all this Land for the Houſe of God, that his Miniſters ſhall be encouraged to ſet
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154625:26"/>themſelves with all cheerfulneſſe about the ſalvation of the peoples ſouls: Your Honors wil ſo provide it, that the Paſtors ſhall have nothing to do but with God and with ſouls, and with devils, to hold off by their Spirituall weapons theſe roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lions from their flocks: queſtionles your Pieties will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſo much due reſpect, and ſo honorable a maintenance for every ſervant of God in this land, that without diſquietnes of minde, or ſolicitude for the things of this world, they may wait wholly on their Spirituall Charges: The Pagan Princes of old, the Turkiſh this day, the ancient Popiſh Parliaments, and the late Prelaticall, have demonſtrate their care for that which they eſteemed the ſervice of their God: it will be very far from this moſt hopefull of all Parliaments, for which the Lord hath already done ſo many and ſo great things, which alſo for time to come hath ſo much need of the ſpeciall aſſiſtance, and ſingular help of God, that they ſhould in this ſo naturall, ſo reaſonable, ſo Chriſtian a Duty towards the ſervants of God, be any ways lacking. Moſt wiſely, and with all reaſon, have they procured the Lamps of the Houſe of God to be ſet in ſuch poſture, as their light may beſt ſhine to the uſe of men: Starres, though otherwiſe great, and full of light, if they move in too high a Sphear, become either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, or of an obſcure and bad light, for little uſe to men below upon earth: The Paſtors of Gods Houſe, when they ſtand too high in worldly pomp above the people, their light in ſo great a diſtance vaniſheth, and ſcarce is viſible to men ſo far below them. Yet it would be carefully conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That the Lights of the Houſe of God be not too much brought down, and ſet too low; to put them <hi>under a buſhell,</hi> to ſet them under the feet of the family, were to mar their ſhine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hinder the communication of their light.</p>
            <p>Above all, great care would be uſed, that when the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity of Oil which did choke and extinguiſh, rather then maintain the light of ſome Lamps, ſhall be diverted unto bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter employment, nevertheleſſe that no Candle of God, in any part of this Land, be permitted to languiſh, much leſſe to die for want of ſo much Oil as is requiſite for a convenient ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:154625:26"/>But a word to wiſe men, and half a word of this kinde to men ſo religious, and zealous for the Houſe of God, is enough.</p>
            <p>So much for the Impediments which Satan made to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Sion: Now follows their Removall, in the which are three things, <hi>i.</hi> A Preface, <hi>The Lord ſaid unto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">A Paraphraſe on the ſecond verſe.</note> The Mean whereby theſe Impediments were remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and that Oppoſition quaſht, Chriſts curſing of Satan, or his prayer to the Father to rebuke and repreſſe him. 3. Two Reaſons of this Rebuke, 1. <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> election, then her great ſufferings. For ſhortneſſe, we ſhall onely give a brief Paraphraſe of all the words together, without long expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And for Doctrine, we ſhall touch but on ſome few Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, which for Uſe we ſhall remit to your own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation.</p>
            <p>As for the Preface, <hi>The Lord ſaid unto Satan:</hi>
               <note place="margin">How Spirits can ſpeak.</note> Angels and devils communicate with God, and one with another, not by ſpeeches, for Language requires bodily inſtruments, which theſe Spirits want: but as they apprehend every object with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſenſes, ſo they expreſſe what they have apprehended with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Language, in a way above our humane nature, which we do not underſtand. However, in this place, and elſewhere oft, where by way of Viſion the communication of one Spirit with another is repreſented, for our apprehenſion all is ſet done in ſpeeches, as the ordinary way wherein men commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate their thoughts one to another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord ſaid unto Satan:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt the Lord.</note> He who before was called an Angel, is here named the Lord, even Chriſt, as we ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Lord and Creator of all, the Heir (even as he is man) of all; for <hi>there is one God, and one Lord,</hi> the man Jeſus,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.6.</note> to whom the Father hath given a Name above all names, and hath ſet all things under his feet, Principalities and Powers themſelves to be his ſervants, and he their Lord and God.</p>
            <p>The matter of his ſpeech is an Invocation of the Father to reprove Satan: The Lord ſpeaketh to the Lord,
<note place="margin">The Lord ſpeaketh to the Lord. Pſal. 110 1.</note> the Son to the Father: ſo the words of the Pſalm are to be taken, <hi>The Lord ſaid unto my Lord, Sit thou at my right hand:</hi> And that of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154625:27"/>
               <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19 24.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord rained down fire upon Sodom from the Lord.</hi> The Son leadeth to the Father, as to the fountain of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and all divine Operations; which importeth no diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Eſſence, Subſtance, or Matter in the Trinity, but onely a diſtinction of Perſons, and an heavenly Order in theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as in Being, ſo in Operation; The Father being the firſt, The Son the ſecond, The Spirit the third; but all equally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite in Glory, Power, Eternity, and all divine Attributes; in theſe there is no inequality, no poſteriority among them: This now is to be believed from divers Scriptures, but not to be thorowly underſtood, till afterwards, when we ſhall ſee God, as we are ſeen of him.</p>
            <p>The rebuking of Satan imports not onely a bitter and ſharp reproof of his malice,
<note place="margin">What is the rebuking of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.</note> to his confuſion and ſhame, but alſo a reſtraint and cohibition of his power, by the mercifull and ſtrong hand of the Father. This is repeated, becauſe of Chriſt his zeal to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> welfare, and his deteſtation of Satans wicked deſignes againſt her.</p>
            <p>The firſt Reaſon of that Reproof is, The Lords chuſing of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to be the place of his Worſhip,
<note place="margin">The firſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke.</note> and Habitation of his Church: Satan had the reſt of the earth for his ſervice; but, not content herewith, that one place which the Lords Election had reſerved for his own little Flock, the malice of that unreaſonable ſpirit would not leave to God.</p>
            <p>The other reaſon,
<note place="margin">The ſecond Reaſon.</note> That ſame one place, that one poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which God had choſen out of all the families of the earth to be his peculiar Treaſure, had been caſt in the fiery furnace of heavie tribulation, and was but lately drawn out of the fire; that mercileſſe ſpirit the devill, nothing ſatisfied with all the miſeries of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> went about to procure her utter deſtruction, and burning down to aſhes, that ſo on the whole earth there ſhould have been left none at all to ſerve the Lord: But Chriſt remembring his Election, and having compaſſion upon their former ſufferings, defendeth their Cauſe, poureth ſhame on the malice of Satan, reſtraineth his power, chaſeth him away, that he may no longer retard the welfare of his people.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:154625:27"/>
            <p>From the Preface,
<note place="margin">The firſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, Chriſt his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful patience towards the very devill.</note> obſerve the great patience and long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of Chriſt; he holdeh his peace long, and when he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at laſt to Satan, it is but to rebuke him. This evil ſpirit had ſeduced and deſtroyed the ſouls well-neer of the whole world, he ſtandeth here before the Lord for to ſwallow up the ſmall remnant: Did not ſuch horrible wickedneſſe require a preſent deſtruction from the Lords hand? and not a reproof onely from his mouth.</p>
            <p>Conſider well the Lord his way of proceeding with all the wicked, both men and devils: There is a time appointed for their full deſtruction, and till that day come, the Lord hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his peace; or if he break out in words or deeds againſt them, it is but in a ſmall degree of wrath, in compariſon of what is following. Satan is reſerved in chains till the laſt day, where he is to be bound, and caſt in the lake: One of theſe ſpirits could ſay unto Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Matth. 8.29.</note> 
               <hi>Art thou come to torment us before the time?</hi> When the wicked are moſt proud and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent, God <hi>laugheth at them, for he ſecth their day is coming;</hi> the day of their vengeance, the yeer of recompences, the morning, the hour of their calamity.</p>
            <p>All of us would conſider the ſtate of our ſoul, the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations which conſcience telleth us we are guilty of: think them not forgotten with God, though he keep ſilence, and permit us to go on in the ways of our own heart, without trouble; or if he reprove, it is but by his Word; Now and then in the publike Miniſtery chopping upon the ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and half dead heart: You ſee in this place he dealeth no otherwiſe with the very devil; but be perſwaded there is a time coming for a more ſevere reckoning. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> is often to be read by a ſecure people, the ſixth verſe, <hi>An end is come, the end is come, it watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for thee; behold, it is come, the morning is come upn thee, the time is come, the day of trouble is neer, and not the ſounding of the mountains:</hi> In that one verſe the coming of the day of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is five or ſix times proclaimed: Happy are theſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:154625:28"/>who make uſe of the day of their mercifull Viſitation: The Lord hath been wonderfully good to us; the War hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the eſtates of many thouſands, the Sword hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved many of their lives, we are yet ſafe; but can we tell how long? manage well this happy day of grace, humble your ſoul before the Lord, make peace with him without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay; mourn for your known faults; ſet your ſelves to amend the evil of your doings, that you may be ſpared in the fearfull day of the Lords wrath, when the ſword of the field, the famine and peſtilence of the City, may make ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock of people without number. Bleſſed are they, who after ſo many warnings from the mouth of God in his Word, from the hand of God in his Works, have learned at laſt to be wiſe for their own great good.</p>
            <p>Upon the Reproof,
<note place="margin">The ſecond Obſervation, Chriſts rebuk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill will bring us to a victory over all our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</note> obſerve firſt, The onely way to remove all impediments and oppoſitions to the reparation of a Church and State, is Chriſt his interceſſion with the Father againſt the devill. That which hindered <hi>Jeſhua</hi> and <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel</hi> to build the Temple, to fortifie <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was that active ſpirit, which moved and ſtirred up all the malignant inſtruments that appeared againſt them: The Jews till this time were never able to overcome their enemies; but behold, ſo ſoon as Chriſt taketh the work in hand, ſo ſoon as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buketh and reſtraineth Satan the principall enemy, inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent all the inferiour inſtruments on earth, all theſe malignant men and women did fail and ſuccumb, they were no more able to trouble Gods people in their work.</p>
            <p>This is the ground of our hope and comfort,
<note place="margin">The oppoſers of the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of our Church.</note> in the midſt of ſo huge difficulties as this day on all ſides beſet us, how ſhall our Sion be gotten builded? when we look to the oppoſers, their ſtrength is exceeding great, a mighty faction of declared Papiſts, a great number of Epiſcopall Clergie, and people openly joyning with Papiſts againſt us, and both avowedly ſupported by Soveraign Authority: Alſo a multitude of Sects, Anabaptiſts, Antinomians, Separatiſts, and others, puſhed on by a deluded conſcience, to oppoſe with all their skill, with all their might, all ſolid Reformation: beſide all
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:154625:28"/>the former, a great number in all ranks and eſtates, profane and looſe perſons, exceeding unwilling to behold the ſetling of any Order which may controll them with any power in their wonted licentiouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Concerning the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The oppoſers of the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of our State.</note> the eſtabliſhing of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Peace in the Civill State; with what inſuperable difficulties this work is compaſſed, wofull experience doth teach. A mighty faction of lawleſſe men, who have drawn away, partly by perſwaſion, and partly by force, a great part of the people, the greateſt part of the Nobles, and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Authority it ſelf: this faction of it ſelf very potent, is alſo ſupported with the help that forraign friends are able to afford: and, which is more then all yet named, and more terrible then all fleſh and blood, we have to do with Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and Powers, who act and guide, with all the craft and force they are able, our humane adverſaries: And, which is yet the greateſt ſtrength of all, the grievous ſins of the Land, which provoke the Lord God to be on the ſide of our enemies, men and devils, to ſtrengthen their arm againſt us.</p>
            <p>The ſight of theſe mountains of Impediments would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the ſtouteſt heart,
<note place="margin">Our Comfort againſt both.</note> if above them all we did not ſee our mercifull high Prieſt intreating the Father for the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſins, for the rebuking of Satan, with all vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: the favour we know the Son hath with the Father, will make him obtain all his deſires. Surely, when theſe are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, when the ſins of the Land are remitted, and Satan re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, all other impediments will ſoon be removed: when the ſoul is ſeparate from the body, the members languiſh, and cannor more ſtir: when Chriſt hath confounded Satan, men his inſtruments will quickly either be perſwaded, or forced to reaſon: It is in vain to deal with men, ſo long as a malign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ſpirit prevaileth over them: The ſtreams will run till the fountain be ſtopped: Our firſt and main labour would be with Chriſt, to reſtrain Satan, for he is the life that vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, he the ſpirit that ſtirres up all our oppoſites both in Church and State.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:154625:29"/>
            <p>Obſerve againe how Chriſt in his debate with Satan,
<note place="margin">A third obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Ioh. 8.50. Ioh. 10 30. 1 Ioh. 5.7.</note> hath recourſe to the Father, that he would rebuke him, <hi>The Sonne honoureth the Father, he ſeeketh not his owne glory, but the honour of the Father, The Father and the Son are one,</hi> for all theſe three that witneſſe in Heaven, the Father, the Son, and the Spirit, are one true God; Yet this is the order of the Divine Perſons, that the Father is the firſt, the Sonne and the Spirit are both from him, The Sonne from Eternity begotten of him, The Spirit from Eternity proceeding from him and from the Sonne.</p>
            <p>So long as the vaile of Fleſh covereth the eyes of our Soule, we muſt not enquire too curiouſly in this unſearchable My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery:
<note place="margin">1 Kings 19.13.</note> 
               <hi>Elias wrapped his face in his Mantle when the Lord paſſed by him:</hi> God will not be gazed upon, he diſchargeth it expreſly under the pain of death.
<note place="margin">Exod. 19.21.</note> The malapart and Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent boldneſſe of ſundry Divines, ſubjecting to the foul feet of their idle ſpeculations, the deepeſt and moſt unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible Myſteries of the holy Trinitie, is juſtly plagued with evident and fooliſh errour: Their eyes who will gaze on the Sun in the noon day, cannot but be dazled; and if that madneſſe continue, blindnes and excaecation inavoidable will follow: Faith here, if any where, is the Mother of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, The companion of ſimplicitie and reverence; it ſetteth us limits at the foot of the Mountain in a farre diſtance,
<note place="margin">Exod. 19.23.</note> which we muſt not break through: When we do behold with the moſt open face,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> the Godhead, we muſt be looking on our Glaſſe; the eye muſt never wander from the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Word: Onely what we ſee of God, let it be holden faſt againſt all contradiction. Worſhip the Father, the Son, and the Spirit; one true God, three truely diſtinct Perſons, whereof the Father is the firſt, the Son the ſecond; This Perſon alone is incarnate, uniting in the fulneſſe of time to his Divine Perſon, the nature of Man: The holy Ghoſt is the third, and yet all three are equall in Glory, in Eternitie, and every Divine attribute.</p>
            <p>Hold faſt in thy minde theſe plain Catechetick Scripturall Notions of God: Beware to make to thy ſelf an Idoll in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154625:29"/>thy brain, to frame a falſe, erroneous and unwritten concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the true God: If thou worſhip the Trinity as three divers Gods, thou becomeſt a Pagan, aboliſhing, by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Gods, the Unity of the divine Nature: If thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend God ſo much one, as not three Perſons, thou turneſt Turk, a Jew, an old Arian and Macedonian Heretike; and, which is all theſe in one, a Socinian, a reall Atheiſt: for it is Chriſts own Concluſion, <hi>Who honoureth not the Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5 23.</note> 
               <hi>honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the Father, which hath ſent him.</hi> The neglect, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, the denyall of any one Perſon, reflecteth alike on all the three, and the whole God-head.</p>
            <p>A third Obſervation upon the Reproof, if time did permit,
<note place="margin">A fourth Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</note> would be the holy and gracious practice of Chriſt in his hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt zeal; he bringeth no falſe,
<note place="margin">2 Pet 1.11.</note> no <hi>railing accuſation</hi> againſt the devill himſelf; the fartheſt he goeth againſt this arch-enemy, is to commit him to God to be rebuked: Lyes, calumnies, railings agianſt the devill are inexcuſable, and would not be countenanced: It is a fooliſh policy, and a profane zeal, to advance the Cauſe of God by the arts of the devill: Lying calumnies, malicious bitterneſſe, are helliſh weapons; a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hand muſt not take them up, were it againſt their very author: The Arſenall of God is not ſo unprovided of lawfull Arms, his Quiver not ſo disfurniſhed of his own Arrows, that we need go borrow from <hi>Askelon</hi> or <hi>Gath,</hi> from hell it ſelf, theſe poyſoned Darts, dipped in the venome of Aſps, in the blood of that old Serpent, the father of Lyes, the great Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniator from the beginning.</p>
            <p>A fourth Obſervation;
<note place="margin">A fifth Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</note> God rebuketh Satan before his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deſtruction; his children in this are heirs to their father; After a little time, death will put all the wicked in a full poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of their inheritance; their ſouls firſt; and after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, their bodies alſo ſhall be placed in theſe lakes of fire: but before, they are to be infeoffed and ſeized; they are to have the earneſt of their fathers portion; they are to be rebuked of God, their ſecret wickedneſſe is to be brought to light, their well-covered villanies to be proclaimed on the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:154625:30"/>houſe tops; ſhame and confuſion to be poured on their faces; their malice and violence is to be reſtrained, their puſhing horns to be hammered off, by the Carpenters; Satan and they will bee coopt up within ſo narrow a circle, and bee bound with ſo ſhort a chain, that all may underſtand they are rebuked of God.</p>
            <p>Alſo it would be a comfortable conſideration to meditate on the zeal of Chriſt for <hi>Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A ſixth Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</note> againſt all her enemies: He ſpeaketh here as a man in a paſſion, repeating and ingemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his angry words. <hi>The Lord rebuke thee, even the Lord rebuke thee:</hi> The Lord proclaimeth the ſounding of his Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, before he got Fleſh; the tenderneſſe of his compaſſion towards the Church, before his Incarnation. Certainly, the ſympathie of his heart, and his fellow feeling with us in all our afflictions, is not now diminiſhed, but rather (if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) increaſed after his experimentall knowledge on the earth, in his own perſon, of theſe evils which Satan and wicked men inflict upon the godly.</p>
            <p>From the Reaſons which the Lord uſeth for Satans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof,
<note place="margin">A ſeventh</note> we may behold the Devill his end, and intention in moleſting of <hi>Joſhua;</hi> the thing he ſeeketh is the overthrow of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Satan driveth moſt at the everſion of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like;
<note place="margin">Phil. 2 21.</note> Therefore the preſervation of the publike ought to go neereſt our heart: <hi>Many ſeek their own things, and not thoſe of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> They minde themſelves much more, then either Church or State. This ſelf-wiſedom is fooliſh, for if the Ship wherein thou ſaileſt, be drowned, what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thy Goods; if the houſe wherein thou art locked, be burnt, how ſhall thy life be ſaved.</p>
            <p>From the firſt Reaſon the chooſing of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> obſerve,
<note place="margin">An eighth.</note> That Election is a principall ground of comfort againſt all Satans tentations. True, the difference is wide betwixt a nationall and perſonall Election, betwixt the choice of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> or any other place to be the ſeat and habitation of the Church; and betwixt the Election of perſons to grace and glory: This I may not ſtand to cleer, onely ſtrive to make
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:154625:30"/>our perſonall Election ſure; for upon the grounded aſſurance thereof, we come to a glorious confidence, that no creature, neither Satan, nor the World, nor conſcience, nor any other ſhall ever be able to confound us?
<note place="margin">Rom 8.33.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect? It is God that juſtifieth: Who is he that condemneth: It is Chriſt that dyed.</hi> One of the ſweeteſt private fruits of ſuch a dayes exerciſe, is to get our calling, and our Election ſealed: Verily, a penitent ſoul who throughly hath mourned for ſin, and fled to Chriſt for mercy; who hath gotten of his ſpirit for a reall and ſincere beginning of a through Sanctification, and amendment in every thing, which either within or without hath been amiſſe: A ſoul this farre proceeded in Grace, uſeth to receive the ſtamp of the Spirit; The inward unction and witneſſe, that they are the Sons of God, Elect, and called; who ſhall be glorified,
<note place="margin">Rom 8.17. 2 Pet. 1.11.</note> after they have ſuffered a while, to ſuch an entrance uſeth to be miniſtred aboundantly into the everlaſting Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>From the laſt Reaſon, take but ſome few brief notes.
<note place="margin">An ninth.</note> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the Church of God, and <hi>Joſhua</hi> the chief Member of it for the time, were like a Stick half burnt in the fire of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivitie: Out of that fire they were pulled in Gods mercy, to be preſerved againſt all the malicious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of Satan, and his inſtruments. From hence you ſee the beſt beloved people of God, by the Devill and wicked men, may be brought exceeding low, and ſo neer to utter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as a ſtick burning in the fire, is to Aſhes: So it was with <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in <hi>Babel,</hi> and oft elſewhere. We therefore in our moſt deſperate caſes, muſt not deſpair;
<note place="margin">Exod 3 2. Iſai 43 2. Dan. 3.25.</note> 
               <hi>The burning Buſh will not be conſumed,</hi> God hath promiſed to be with us, in fire and water: One like the Son of man walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the fiery Furnace with the three Children. When to the eye of the World our condition is moſt deſperate, when ſence maketh us cry out,
<note place="margin">Lam. 3.48.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> 
               <hi>My ſtrength and my hope is periſhed from the Lord, They have cut of my life in the dungeon, and caſt a ſtone upon me;</hi> yet faith will quickly correct ſence, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:154625:31"/>make us ſubjoyn; it is good for a man to have hope, and quietly to wait for ſalvation of the Lord;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.13.</note> and when we are <hi>lying among the Pots,</hi> to wait for the time, when we <hi>ſhall be as the Wings of the Dove, covered with ſilver, and her Feathers with yellow gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">The tenth.</note> Conſider the exceeding great terrour of God, when he is angry, his wrath burneth like fire; It maketh the green tree to be like a burnt ſtick, what will it do to the dry; It maketh the moſt godly to become <hi>like a bottle in the ſmoak;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.83 Pſal. 22.15. Pſal 32 4.</note> It dryeth up their ſtrength like a Potſheard; It turneth their <hi>moiſture into the draught of Summer,</hi> knowing the terrour of the Lord be perſwaded to make peace with him in time; ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not on his hot diſpleaſure. The taſting of the forbidden Aple will coſt thee wonderfull dear, Though (which yet in the act of ſin, without madneſſe cannot be ſuppoſed) thou ſhould be certain to eſcape Hell.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">The eleventh.</note> The Church here is a Brand pulled out of the fire, a fire-brand to burn her enemies to Aſhes, it is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unhappy to be an inſtrument of the Churches trouble. Though God be angry with his people, and he be very juſt in caſting them in the fiery Furnace of his wrath, yet woe to all theſe who are Bellows, or Fewell to that fire, who do vex the Church in any way. Our Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> in his twelfth Chapter ſheweth, That to all theſe who had taken up <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the people of God, to caſt them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from their habitation, as a ſtone out of a ſling. To all theſe,
<note place="margin">Joh. 12.3.</note> I ſay, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> became a heavy, and a burdenſome ſtone, to cut and to cruſh them in pieces. Her Neighbours thought to have ſwallowed her down quick, and to have drunk her off as a potion of ſweet Wine; but ſhe becometh to them <hi>a Cup of trembling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 12.2.</note> a draught of poyſon, which maketh them tremble, ſtagger, and fall without riſing; and which is the Metaphor of our Text, The people of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>a torch of fire in a Sheaff,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 12.6.</note> 
               <hi>to devour all their enemies round about, on the right hand and on the left.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nebuchad-nezzars</hi> Image, when the little ſtone did fall
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:154625:31"/>upon its feet, was not onely broken all to pieces,
<note place="margin">Dan. 2.25.</note> but alſo made like the chaff, and was carryed away ſo violently by the winde, that no place was found for any part thereof: All the perſecuters of the Saints have miſcarryed for this cauſe, above any other: The greateſt Monarchies and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms that have been upon the earth, are vaniſhed, and no re-likes of them appear this day. None who are wiſe will touch the people of the Lord, for they are the <hi>apple of Gods eye,</hi> the hurt whereof he cannot but avenge. It is extreme dangerous to be employed by God himſelf in the chaſtiſing of his children; for uſually when the Lord returneth in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to embrace his chaſtiſed childe, the rods of his anger, and ſtaves of his indignation are caſt in the fire,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 10.5.16, 17.</note> till they be burnt to aſhes.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, conſider the mercifull reaſoning of the Angel:
<note place="margin">The laſt.</note> 
               <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> is a brand well-near conſumed in the fire of Gods wrath, and therefore ought to be pitied, and freed from fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trouble. How extremely contrary is this to Satans lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, and his inſtruments concluſions? they adde affliction to the moſt afflicted; they preſſe moſt the godly, when they finde them weakeſt, and on the brink of ruine; we have their language in the 71 <hi>Pſa.</hi> 11. <hi>God hath forſaken him, perſecute and take him, for there is none to deliver him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 83 4.</note> It is then when they ſay, <hi>Come, and let us eut them off from being a Nation, that the name of Iſrael be no more in remembrance.</hi> Long ſufferings, and extreme miſery are to Satan and wicked men provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of further perſecution; but to God they be arguments of favour and deliverance: Hence it is, that the godly lay out before the face of God in their mourning their ſufferings to the full, as moſt pregnant incitements to compaſſion: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and ſee if there be any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow which is done unto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan 9.12.</note> 
               <hi>under the whole heaven hath not been done as hath been done upon Jeruſalem.</hi> The Lord alloweth us to ſpread out before him all the matter of our preſent grief, and of our future fears, hereby, as it were, to ſtir up the compaſſionate
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:154625:32"/>bowells of his mercy: We would be crying to him, not onely to pull the tree of our Church and State out of that fire which hath already burnt up very many Branches, and is like, if not quickly quenched, to go to the very Root; but further we would be earneſt for that burnt ſtick, when it is pull'd out of the flame, that the dews of heaven, and the Sun-ſhine of divine favour, may fall ſo plentifully upon it, that it may yet again flouriſh, and bring forth fruits better and more abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant then ever, and it may become a pleaſant and fruitfull Vine, under whoſe ſhadow we all may lie down in peace, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the bleſſings of God, and ſinging with a loud voyce his praiſes for our deliverance from all our preſent afflictions.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154625:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
